const arr = [{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 35-year-old man with a history of intravenous (IV) drug abuse has generalized lymphadenopathy. Which of the following tests would help in finding the cause of his lymphadenopathy?","answers":[{"option":"Histopathology","bool":false},{"option":"HIV serology","bool":true},{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasonography","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow biopsy","bool":false}],"id":0},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A cord blood sample of an Rh-ve mother was sent for laboratory testing during labor. Which of the following would indicate the need for blood exchange transfusion?","answers":[{"option":"Hemoglobin = 10 mg/dL","bool":false},{"option":"Indirect coombs test is weakly negative","bool":false},{"option":"Peripheral cells shows spherocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyte is corrected to 7%","bool":true},{"option":"Serum bilirubin = 2.5 mg/dL","bool":false}],"id":1},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the surest sign to determine that hanging was ante-mortem, rather than post-mortem?","answers":[{"option":"Hyperaemia of trachea and epiglottis","bool":true},{"option":"Cyanosis of face and lips","bool":false},{"option":"Ligature around the neck","bool":false},{"option":"Protruding tongue","bool":false},{"option":"Fracture of hyoid bone","bool":false}],"id":2},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 9-year-old boy presents to the emergency department with left-sided hemiplegia. There is no history of head trauma to explain this presentation. If he had been diagnosed with anemia a few months ago, which of the following accounts for hemiplegia?","answers":[{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Multiple myeloma","bool":false},{"option":"Fainting due to anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false}],"id":3},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Through which of the following bones age and sex determination of a skeleton can be determined?","answers":[{"option":"Metacarpals","bool":false},{"option":"Vertebrae","bool":false},{"option":"Skull and mandible","bool":true},{"option":"Ribs","bool":false},{"option":"Radius and ulna","bool":false}],"id":4},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following conditions is recombinant erythropoietin indicated for?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia due to chronic kidney disease","bool":true},{"option":"Anemia due to thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia due to malnutrition","bool":false}],"id":5},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"What is the advantage of fingerprinting?","answers":[{"option":"It enables absolute identification of an individual","bool":true},{"option":"It is applicable for all people","bool":false},{"option":"It does not require any special and expensive instruments","bool":false},{"option":"It is applicable for all age groups","bool":false},{"option":"No special training required","bool":false}],"id":6},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Spontaneous bleeding becomes evident when the platelet count falls below which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"60,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"40,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"100,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"75,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":false},{"option":"20,000 platelets per microliter blood","bool":true}],"id":7},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the first immediate sign after death?","answers":[{"option":"Stiffening","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary relaxation","bool":false},{"option":"Rigor mortis","bool":false},{"option":"Putrefaction","bool":false},{"option":"Primary relaxation","bool":true}],"id":8},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A guy who shoots himself tends to get instantaneous rigor instead of rigor mortis. Which one of the following statements most likely signifies the difference between the two?","answers":[{"option":"Muscle contraction is less marked in instantaneous rigor mortis","bool":false},{"option":"Instantaneous rigor indicates time of death instead of mode of death","bool":false},{"option":"Instantaneous rigor affects all the muscles","bool":false},{"option":"Primary relaxation is absent in instantaneous rigor mortis","bool":true},{"option":"Instantaneous rigor mortis is not immediate after the death","bool":false}],"id":9},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A dead body is found by a group of people near the station. It is concluded that 6 to 10 hours have passed since the time of death. Which one of the following is most likely to be developed by this time in the body?","answers":[{"option":"Postmortem caloricity","bool":false},{"option":"Potassium increase in CSF","bool":false},{"option":"Postmortem lividity","bool":true},{"option":"Instantaneous rigor","bool":false},{"option":"Rigor mortis","bool":false}],"id":10},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following antibodies are present in Bernard-Soulier syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Glycoprotein Ib/IIIb antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Glycoprotein IIa","bool":false},{"option":"Glycoprotein IIa/IIIb antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Glycoprotein Ib antibodies","bool":true},{"option":"Platelet membrane phospholipids","bool":false}],"id":11},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"The postmortem sign of 'cattle trucking' is seen in which organ?","answers":[{"option":"Cornea","bool":false},{"option":"Brain","bool":false},{"option":"Limbs","bool":false},{"option":"Heart","bool":false},{"option":"Retina","bool":true}],"id":12},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2022","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 13-year-old female presents to the outpatient department (OPD) with on and off menorrhagia, bleeding gums, and petechial rashes. Her laboratory reports show the following results; Hb= 12.5 g/dl, platelet count= 350,000/mm3, activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT)= 49s (normal: 29-40s). Which of the following could be the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":true},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic microangiopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false}],"id":13},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 5-year-old boy comes to the outpatient department complaining of a painful and swollen knee. On examination, bleeding is seen within the knee joint but with no signs of physical trauma. His mother gives a family history of a maternal uncle who recently died of a bleeding disorder. Investigations show isolated increased APTT. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia C","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":true}],"id":14},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the most correct statement regarding an allograft?","answers":[{"option":"A graft performed between different species","bool":false},{"option":"An organ or tissue transplanted from one individual to another","bool":true},{"option":"A graft placed in its normal position","bool":false},{"option":"A graft taken from the same individual","bool":false},{"option":"A graft placed in a site different from that where the organ is normally located","bool":false}],"id":15},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the mechanism of action of alteplase?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibits coagulation factor VIII","bool":false},{"option":"Activates tissue plasminogen to plasmin","bool":true},{"option":"Causes vasodilation","bool":false},{"option":"Decreases cAMP","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of glycoprotein IIb/IIIa","bool":false}],"id":16},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 65-year-old male presents with a 2-month history of fever and weight loss. On examination, the spleen is palpable 6 cm below the left costal margin. Complete blood count (CBC) reveals leukocytes=125x10⁹/L, hemoglobin=7.0 gm/dL and platelets= 510X10³/µL . He is diagnosed with chronic myeloid leukemia. Which of the following defects is present in chronic myeloid leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"t(9:11)","bool":false},{"option":"t(9:22)","bool":true},{"option":"t(8:21)","bool":false},{"option":"t(15:17)","bool":false},{"option":"t(11:21)","bool":false}],"id":17},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Putrefaction is said to be colliquative when there is which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Colour change at right iliac fossa","bool":false},{"option":"Swollen, puffy, bloated face","bool":false},{"option":"Tissue conversion into solid mass","bool":false},{"option":"Appearance of maggots","bool":true},{"option":"Distention of abdominal cavity","bool":false}],"id":18},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"The process of decomposition in the air is twice as rapid as in water and eight times as rapid as in the soil this is called?","answers":[{"option":"Casper's dictum","bool":true},{"option":"Fudin's principle","bool":false},{"option":"Newton law","bool":false},{"option":"Locard's exchange principle","bool":false},{"option":"Siphon principle","bool":false}],"id":19},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2022","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 25-year-old male presents to the clinic with easy fatigability and generalized weakness. On examination he has blood pressure (BP)=110/60 mm of Hg, looks pale, and has koilonychia. His complete blood count (CBC) shows: Hb=9.7 g/dl, MCV=69 fl, MCHC=26 g/dl. What is the most likely cause of anemia in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Thalassemia major","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia minor","bool":false}],"id":20},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A fresh victim of a road traffic accident is brought to the emergency department but lost his life on the\r\nway to the hospital. To confirm his death, the body is examined for all immediate signs of death. Which of\r\nthe following is an immediate sign of death?","answers":[{"option":"Primary relaxation","bool":true},{"option":"Rigor Mortis","bool":false},{"option":"Postmortem lividity","bool":false},{"option":"Algor mortis","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary relaxation","bool":false}],"id":21},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A decapitated dead body of a male is brought for autopsy. What will be the most important part of an autopsy in this case for further identification?","answers":[{"option":"Preservation of 1st vertebra of the body distal to the cut","bool":false},{"option":"Taking photographs","bool":false},{"option":"Taking bone marrow for DNA fingerprinting","bool":false},{"option":"Taking poor prints","bool":false},{"option":"Taking fingerprints of the body","bool":true}],"id":22},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A boy is convicted of a criminal offense and the judge of the juvenile court orders to send him to a reformatory school. This is because his age is less than which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"17 years","bool":false},{"option":"15 years","bool":false},{"option":"18 years","bool":true},{"option":"16 years","bool":false},{"option":"14 years","bool":false}],"id":23},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"The age of a young boy needs to be determined. Dental X-ray reveals mixed dentition and examination of the oral cavity reveals that the first molars have erupted. What is the approximate age of this boy?","answers":[{"option":"5-7 years","bool":false},{"option":"6-7 years","bool":true},{"option":"10-12 years","bool":false},{"option":"16-18 years","bool":false},{"option":"6-9 years","bool":false}],"id":24},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"The approximate age of a girl needs to be determined as ordered by the court. After getting a series of X-rays done, it is revealed that she has only 3 carpal bones ossified. What is the likely age of the girl?","answers":[{"option":"10","bool":false},{"option":"3","bool":true},{"option":"1","bool":false},{"option":"7","bool":false},{"option":"6","bool":false}],"id":25},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is not a characteristic feature of hemolytic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Increased neutrophil count","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced plasma haptoglobin level","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased reticulocyte count","bool":true},{"option":"Increased unconjugated bilirubin","bool":false},{"option":"Excess urinary urobilinogen","bool":false}],"id":26},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 2-year-old male child presented in emergency with sudden onset of jaundice and cola-colored urine since last night. He was put on antimalarial two days back for suspected malaria. On examination in addition to jaundice, he has anemia and splenomegaly without hepatomegaly or lymphadenopathy. His blood pressure is 80/50 mmHg, pulse rate 110/min, and no edema. What test will confirm \r\n a diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Liver function test","bool":false},{"option":"Osmotic fragility test","bool":false},{"option":"G6PD levels in red blood cells","bool":true},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":false},{"option":"Urine D/R","bool":false}],"id":27},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A 25-year-old man is being transfused with whole blood. Suddenly, he develops a fever of 38.5°C associated with chills and flushing. Blood is oozing from the cannula site. What kind of transfusion reaction is it?","answers":[{"option":"Allergic reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Acute hemolytic transfusion reaction","bool":true},{"option":"Delayed hemolytic transfusion reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Post transfusion purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Febrile non-hemolytic transfusion reaction","bool":false}],"id":28},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"What is the definitive treatment for thalassemia major?","answers":[{"option":"Iron chelation therapy","bool":false},{"option":"Blood transfusion","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow transplantation","bool":true},{"option":"Iron supplementation","bool":false},{"option":"Cryotherapy","bool":false}],"id":29},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is not a feature of polycythemia?","answers":[{"option":"Headache","bool":false},{"option":"Pruritus","bool":false},{"option":"Cyanosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatosplenomegaly","bool":false},{"option":"Hypotension","bool":true}],"id":30},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Mild hypochromic microcytic anemia is associated with which of the following pathologies?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha-thalassemia minor","bool":true},{"option":"Beta-thalassemia major","bool":false},{"option":"Diamond-Blackfan anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin H disease","bool":false}],"id":31},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a cause of neutropenia?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Allergic reaction","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Addison's disease","bool":false},{"option":"Steroids","bool":false}],"id":32},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"In which of the following conditions will eosinophilia be observed?","answers":[{"option":"Septic shock","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Cushing's syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Protozoal and parasitic infection","bool":true}],"id":33},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following factors promotes sickling?","answers":[{"option":"Bacterial illness","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperoxia","bool":false},{"option":"Alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hypotonicity","bool":false},{"option":"Dehydration","bool":true}],"id":34},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"During the autopsy of a man, the coroner determines his age to be below sixty due to noting that a skull suture has not yet fused. Which of the following correctly identifies this particular skull suture?","answers":[{"option":"Squamous","bool":true},{"option":"Coronal","bool":false},{"option":"Lambdoid","bool":false},{"option":"Delta","bool":false},{"option":"Saggital","bool":false}],"id":35},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A 4-year-old male child is being evaluated for a bleeding disorder. Family history reveals that his maternal uncle had a similar disorder, but his mother and father had no such problem. What is the mode of transmission of the bleeding disorder in this child?","answers":[{"option":"Co-dominant","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":true},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false}],"id":36},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"In which of the following conditions is streptokinase contraindicated?","answers":[{"option":"DIC","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Acute MI","bool":false},{"option":"DVT","bool":false},{"option":"Pulmonary embolism","bool":false}],"id":37},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following describes the mode of transmission of hemophilia A?","answers":[{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":true},{"option":"X- linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Mitochondrial disease","bool":false}],"id":38},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"What is cheiloscopy used for?","answers":[{"option":"Identification of humans based on lip prints","bool":true},{"option":"Identification of humans based on finger prints","bool":false},{"option":"Identification of humans based on bite patterns","bool":false},{"option":"Identification of humans based on hand prints","bool":false},{"option":"Identification of humans based on foot prints","bool":false}],"id":39},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"When does the pisiform bone begin to ossify?","answers":[{"option":"Between 7.5 and 10 years","bool":false},{"option":"Between 1 and 2 years","bool":false},{"option":"Between 10 and 12 years","bool":true},{"option":"Between 3 and 7 years","bool":false},{"option":"Between 5 and 6 years","bool":false}],"id":40},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 22-year-old African American man went to the hospital to determine if he has sickle cell trait. Which one of the following laboratory tests can be used to detect the presence of hemoglobin S?","answers":[{"option":"Schillings test","bool":false},{"option":"Metabisulfite test","bool":true},{"option":"Coombs test","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose tolerance test","bool":false},{"option":"Osmotic fragility test","bool":false}],"id":41},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following results in sickle cell crisis?","answers":[{"option":"Vaso-occlusive crisis","bool":true},{"option":"Sickling","bool":false},{"option":"Autosplenectomy","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic crisis","bool":false},{"option":"Sequestration crisis","bool":false}],"id":42},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is not classified as a platelet functional disorder?","answers":[{"option":"Bernard soulier syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthemia","bool":false},{"option":"Grey platelet syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenia purpura","bool":true}],"id":43},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"What is the most common cause of macrocytic anaemia?","answers":[{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12/B9 deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin C deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":false}],"id":44},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura can be successfully treated by which of the following methods?","answers":[{"option":"Dialysis which remove auto antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Catheterization which remove plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous infusion which removes the antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet infusion which removes basal cells","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma exchange which remove auto antibodies","bool":true}],"id":45},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following agents directly activates plasminogen?","answers":[{"option":"Tissue plasminogen activator (tPA)","bool":false},{"option":"Urokinase","bool":true},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false}],"id":46},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 16-year-old boy is brought to the clinic with generalized weakness and easy bruising. His complete blood profile shows pancytopenia. Peripheral film shows giant metamyelocytes with large sausage-shaped nuclei. His bilirubin is  3 mg%. The reticulocyte count is 0.5%. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Acute leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false}],"id":47},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common site for extrapulmonary tuberculosis?","answers":[{"option":"Central nervous system","bool":false},{"option":"Pericardium","bool":false},{"option":"Bones and joint","bool":false},{"option":"Gastrointestinal tract","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":true}],"id":48},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A male came to the outpatient department with the complaints of epistaxis and mucosal bleeding. Bleeding time is more than 5 minutes. Factor VIII and VIIIC are reduced. There is a history of similar illness in the family. What is your diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin K deﬁciency","bool":false},{"option":"Haemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Christmas disease","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":true},{"option":"Liver failure","bool":false}],"id":49},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the diagnostic test for Rh incompatibility?","answers":[{"option":"Chorionic villus sampling","bool":false},{"option":"Indirect Coombs test","bool":true},{"option":"Amniocentesis","bool":false},{"option":"Fetal middle cerebral arterial (MCA) doppler","bool":false},{"option":"Direct Coombs test","bool":false}],"id":50},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Bernard-Soulier is an inherited disease having giant, non-functional platelets with thrombocytopenia. What is the inheritance pattern of this disease?","answers":[{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Mitochondrial inheritance","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":true},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":false}],"id":51},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following constituents is present in hemoglobin A (HbA)?","answers":[{"option":"2 zeta and 2 epsilon chains","bool":false},{"option":"2 alpha and 2 gamma chains","bool":false},{"option":"2 alpha and 2 delta chains","bool":false},{"option":"2 delta and 2 gamma chains","bool":false},{"option":"2 alpha and 2 beta chains","bool":true}],"id":52},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following is the most common type of Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Nodular lymphocyte predominant","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocyte rich","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocyte depleted","bool":false},{"option":"Mixed cellularity","bool":false},{"option":"Nodular sclerosis","bool":true}],"id":53},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which component of blood is best for transfusion in case of multiple coagulation factor deficiencies?","answers":[{"option":"Cryoprecipitate","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":true},{"option":"Packed red cells","bool":false},{"option":"Pooled platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Whole blood","bool":false}],"id":54},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following is used as an antidote for heparin?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false},{"option":"Protamine sulfate","bool":true},{"option":"Succimer","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma (FFP)","bool":false}],"id":55},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following blood cells have phagocytic activity?","answers":[{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"Fibroblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocytes","bool":false}],"id":56},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is the mechanism of action of tacrolimus?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibition of inosine monophosphate dehydrogenase","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of calcineurin","bool":true},{"option":"Inhibition of purine synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Destruction of T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of IL-2 action","bool":false}],"id":57},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is the most common gene mutation in alpha thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Nonsense mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Missense mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Splice mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Gene deletion","bool":true},{"option":"Frameshift mutation","bool":false}],"id":58},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A female presented with gingival bleeding, fever, and headache to the outpatient department (OPD). Her lab results showed normal partial thromboplastin time (PTT) and prothrombin time (PT) but increased bleeding time. Her blood smear showed the presence of schistocytes. Which one is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":true},{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false}],"id":59},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Maximum number of Reed-Sternberg cells are seen in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocyte predominant Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocyte depleted Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Burkitt Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Nodular sclerosis Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Mixed cellularity Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":60},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following groups of drugs is not used for the treatment of thrombosis?","answers":[{"option":"Antifibrinolytics","bool":true},{"option":"Anticoagulants","bool":false},{"option":"Antiplatelet drugs","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombin inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinolytics","bool":false}],"id":61},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Stony hard lymph node is mostly suggestive of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberculosis","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Infection","bool":false},{"option":"Malignancy","bool":true}],"id":62},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Patients with severe liver disease are most likely to develop which of the following pathological findings?","answers":[{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Patient will be unresponsive to vitamin K injection","bool":true},{"option":"Defect in Gp1B receptors of platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Normal PT and APTT","bool":false},{"option":"Increased bleeding time","bool":false}],"id":63},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"What is the most common condition leading to disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) in hospitalized patients?","answers":[{"option":"Severe infection","bool":true},{"option":"Snake bite","bool":false},{"option":"Malignancy","bool":false},{"option":"Trauma","bool":false},{"option":"Vascular aneurysms","bool":false}],"id":64},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which iron preparation can be given only by the intravenous route?","answers":[{"option":"Sodium ferrous gluconate complex","bool":false},{"option":"Iron fructose complex","bool":false},{"option":"Sodium ferric gluconate complex","bool":true},{"option":"Ferrous gluconate dessicated","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrous fumarate","bool":false}],"id":65},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the most commonly encountered pattern of fingerprints?","answers":[{"option":"Arch","bool":false},{"option":"Accidental","bool":false},{"option":"Loop","bool":true},{"option":"Composite","bool":false},{"option":"Whorl","bool":false}],"id":66},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which condition shows both arterial and venous thrombosis?","answers":[{"option":"Factor V Leiden mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Protein S deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Antithrombin deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Protein C deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Antiphospholipid antibody syndrome","bool":true}],"id":67},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A patient may present with hemolytic anemia because of genetic mutations in protein synthesis. What is the most common inherited disorder causing anemia in humans in this connection?","answers":[{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":true}],"id":68},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"What is the single best test to confirm iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Plasma iron level","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow biopsy","bool":false},{"option":"Total iron-binding capacity (TIBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin saturation","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma ferritin levels","bool":true}],"id":69},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which one of the following cells is dominant in viral infection?","answers":[{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false}],"id":70},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 10-year-old child is brought to the hospital with complaints of bloody diarrhea for the past 3 days. Examination and labs reveal an acute kidney injury along with thrombocytopenia. Upon taking history, the parents said that their child had an E. coli infection for the past few days. Which one of the following cells is most likely to be seen in this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Heinz bodies","bool":false},{"option":"Bite cells","bool":false},{"option":"Tear drop cells","bool":false},{"option":"Schistocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cells","bool":false}],"id":71},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 30-year-old lady received 6 units of blood and developed carpopedal spasm and twitching in her hands, along with flushing of the face. What can be given to relieve her condition?","answers":[{"option":"Intravenous normal saline","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous water","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous calcium gluconate","bool":true},{"option":"Intravenous 5% dextrose","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous diazepam","bool":false}],"id":72},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following agents is a potent iron chelator?","answers":[{"option":"Succimer","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrous gluconate","bool":false},{"option":"Unithiol","bool":false},{"option":"Deferoxamine","bool":true},{"option":"Ferrous sulfate","bool":false}],"id":73},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Stunted and notched upper central incisors are most likely to be found in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Congenital syphilis","bool":true},{"option":"Scurvy","bool":false},{"option":"Rickets","bool":false},{"option":"Fetal alcohol syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Plummer vinson syndrome","bool":false}],"id":74},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A girl presented to the emergency with a complaint of easy bruising and petechia, which is on and off. Her brother also suffered from the same condition. The lab results of the girl showed increased bleeding and partial thromboplastin time. Which one of the following conditions was she suffering from?","answers":[{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":false},{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":true}],"id":75},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 6-year-old child, diagnosed with hereditary spherocytosis, complained of increased frequency of blood transfusions. Blood complete picture shows Hb=6.5 gm/dL, reticulocyte count=20%, TLC=4000/mm³, platelets=100,000/mm³. What will be the most appropriate treatment for this child?","answers":[{"option":"Corticosteroids with antithymhocytic globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":true},{"option":"Bone marrow transplant","bool":false},{"option":"Hydroxyurea","bool":false},{"option":"Repeated transfusions with iron chelation","bool":false}],"id":76},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is not correct about non-Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Epstein-Barr virus is associated with post-transplant non-Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Males have a slightly higher risk","bool":false},{"option":"Median age is 65-70 years","bool":false},{"option":"Burkitt lymphoma is most aggressive and incurable","bool":true},{"option":"t(14:18) in follicular lymphoma results in dysregulated BCL2 expression","bool":false}],"id":77},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 4-year-old girl presents with skin pallor for the past 3 days. One week ago she had a history of bloody diarrhea. Examination showed petechiae on the upper limbs. Laboratory studies revealed Hb 7.1 g/dl, reticulocytes 14%, platelets 30x 109/L, and normal WBC count. The renal function is deranged. The peripheral smear features numerous schistocytes and occasional nucleated RBC. Given the findings, which of the following bacteria is involved in the pathophysiology of disease?","answers":[{"option":"Salmonella typhi","bool":false},{"option":"Streptococcus pyogenes","bool":false},{"option":"Staphylococcus aureus","bool":false},{"option":"Helicobacter pylori","bool":false},{"option":"Shigella dysenteriae","bool":true}],"id":78},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A child presents with an enlarged spleen and jaundice. His laboratory findings include an increased red blood cell width, spherocytes with loss of pallor, and increased mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC). Which of the following would be a possible diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Myeloproliferative disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":79},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A child suffering from hemolytic uremic syndrome will have which one of the following finding in his peripheral blood smear?","answers":[{"option":"Tear drop RBCs","bool":false},{"option":"Howell-jolly bodies","bool":false},{"option":"Aur rods","bool":false},{"option":"Target cells","bool":false},{"option":"Schistocytes","bool":true}],"id":80},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Why is low molecular weight heparin (LMWH) preferred over unfractionated heparin (UFH)?","answers":[{"option":"LMWH has lesser half life","bool":false},{"option":"LMWH can be given in all conditions","bool":false},{"option":"LMWH has longer half life","bool":true},{"option":"LMWH has no side effects","bool":false},{"option":"LMWH can be taken orally","bool":false}],"id":81},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 22-year-old woman attends an antenatal booking appointment. She has had previous 3 miscarriages. She has mouth ulcers and joint pains and is evaluated for arthritis/ arthralgia. Which single pair of results are most likely to confirm the underlying cause of her symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Increased erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) and rheumatoid factor","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease hemoglobin and increased reticulocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased hemoglobin and decreased mean corpuscular volume (MCV)","bool":false},{"option":"Increased lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) and increased bilirubin","bool":false},{"option":"Increased activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) and decreased platelets","bool":true}],"id":82},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 10-year-old child who is otherwise healthy got a complete blood count done which showed Hb of 10 gm/dL, with hypochromic and microcytic red cell indices. Her pediatrician is assuming her to be a carrier of the beta-thalassemia trait. Which of the following tests will confirm her diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":true},{"option":"Osmotic fragility test","bool":false},{"option":"Blood culture","bool":false},{"option":"Schilling test","bool":false}],"id":83},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"What is the inheritance pattern of glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"Multifactorial","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":true},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false}],"id":84},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A young female presents to the clinic with complaints of exertional dyspnea, fatigue, and diarrhea. Stool examination shows the presence of proglottids. CBC shows Hb = 8 g/dL, MCV = 110, presence of hyper-segmented neutrophils and eosinophilia. The physician is suspecting a worm infection. \r\nWhich of the following species is this patient most likely infected by?","answers":[{"option":"Taenia saginata","bool":false},{"option":"Diphyllobothrium latum","bool":true},{"option":"Ancylostoma duodenale","bool":false},{"option":"Strongyloides stercoralis","bool":false},{"option":"Toxocara canis","bool":false}],"id":85},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"An eye witness claims the victims death occurred about 12 hours ago. Which of the finding will confirm the statement?","answers":[{"option":"Increase in chemical constituents of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)","bool":false},{"option":"Rigor mortis present all over","bool":true},{"option":"Rise in potassium content of vitreous humor","bool":false},{"option":"Greenish patch over caecum","bool":false},{"option":"Lividity fully developed and fixed","bool":false}],"id":86},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 45-year-old male who is bed-bound from paraplegia develops sudden shortness of breath. On examination, his right calf is found to be swollen and tender, a provisional diagnosis of deep vein thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism is made. What will be the single most sought diagnostic test?","answers":[{"option":"Doppler venous ultrasonography","bool":false},{"option":"Echocardiography","bool":false},{"option":"Electrocardiography (ECG)","bool":false},{"option":"X-ray chest","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography (CT) pulmonary angiography","bool":true}],"id":87},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 45-year-old male presents with a 2-month history of fever and weight loss. On examination, massive splenomegaly is observed. Complete blood count (CBC) reveals leukocyte count=165x10⁹/L, hemoglobin= 9.0 gm/dL and platelets=510 X10³/µL . He is diagnosed with chronic myeloid leukemia. Which of the following molecular defects is present in chronic myeloid leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"BCL6 gene fusion","bool":false},{"option":"p53 gene mutation","bool":false},{"option":"RAR alpha (RARA) gene fusion","bool":false},{"option":"BCR-ABL gene fusion","bool":true},{"option":"c-Myc gene fusion","bool":false}],"id":88},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"For the purpose of determining age and sex from the skeleton of an unknown dead body, maximum information can be obtained by examining which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Radius and ulna","bool":false},{"option":"Skull and mandible","bool":true},{"option":"Metacarpals","bool":false},{"option":"Vertebrae","bool":false},{"option":"Ribs","bool":false}],"id":89},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"The dead body of a young female is recovered from her house hanging from a fan. On examination it is seen that post mortem lividity in lower limbs is fully developed and fixed. If, in the dead body, the post mortem lividity does not blanch on applying pressure, what will be the probable time elapsed since her death?","answers":[{"option":"0-3 hours","bool":false},{"option":"6-8 hours","bool":true},{"option":"1-3 hours","bool":false},{"option":"3-6 hours","bool":false},{"option":"10-12 hours","bool":false}],"id":90},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 10-year-old child with a known case of thalassemia major requires red cell transfusion every month, since the age of one year. For the last 5 to 6 months, he develops urticarial rashes during transfusion. What\r\nwill be an appropriate step for management?","answers":[{"option":"Transfuse washed red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Transfuse Rh-negative blood","bool":false},{"option":"Prior to transfusion, give him one shot of steroid","bool":false},{"option":"Transfuse whole blood","bool":false},{"option":"Prior to transfusion, give him antihistamine and antipyretic drugs","bool":true}],"id":91},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"What is the cephalic index?","answers":[{"option":"The ratio of the maximum breadth of the skull and anterioposterior length of skull","bool":true},{"option":"Maximum anteroposterior length of skull","bool":false},{"option":"Sum of the maximum breadth of the skull and the maximum length of skull","bool":false},{"option":"The maximum transverse breadth of skull","bool":false},{"option":"Superimposition technique","bool":false}],"id":92},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A male aged about 16-17 years is sent to confirm his age. Advisable single radiograph would be which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Elbow joint","bool":true},{"option":"Wrist joint","bool":false},{"option":"Skull","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Sternum","bool":false}],"id":93},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"During the exhumation of an unidentified grave, a human skeleton was recovered.  What will be the most reliable bones to determine sex?","answers":[{"option":"Femur","bool":false},{"option":"Skull and pelvis","bool":true},{"option":"Skull and femur","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Skull","bool":false}],"id":94},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Why is parenteral administration of folic acid not favored in patients?","answers":[{"option":"It is too painful through the parenteral route","bool":false},{"option":"It is rapidly metabolized and eliminated","bool":false},{"option":"Given orally because it is very tasty and hence the patient's compliance is very high","bool":false},{"option":"Its profound deficiency is not seen in human beings","bool":false},{"option":"It is well absorbed orally even in patients with malabsorption syndromes","bool":true}],"id":95},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Different blood products are transfused in different clinical conditions. Which product is required if\r\na patient is bleeding actively and has deficiencies of multiple coagulation factors?","answers":[{"option":"Packed red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":true},{"option":"Cryoprecipitate","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet","bool":false},{"option":"Whole blood","bool":false}],"id":96},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the result of vitamin B12 deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Impaired coagulation","bool":false},{"option":"Impaired hemoglobin synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Impaired DNA synthesis","bool":true},{"option":"Hematopoietic stem cell failure","bool":false},{"option":"Impaired collagen formation","bool":false}],"id":97},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 29-year-old female comes for a routine checkup as part of a pre-employment requirement. Her complete blood count reveals Hb= 10 gm/dL with microcytic hypochromic red cell indices. Assuming that she is a carrier of the beta-thalassemia trait, what will be the most likely findings on her hemoglobin electrophoresis to confirm her carrier status?","answers":[{"option":"Normal HbA and A2, but markedly increased HbF (>90%)","bool":false},{"option":"Normal HbA and A2, but slightly increased HbF","bool":false},{"option":"Normal HbA and increased Hb A2 (4-8%)","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased HbA,and raised HbA2 and HbF","bool":true},{"option":"Normal HbA and increased Hb A2 (3-5%)","bool":false}],"id":98},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 20-year-old male is brought to the outpatient department with a history of painless cervical lymphadenopathy and a physician is suspecting malignancy. What is the key investigation required to get a diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Excisional biopsy of the node","bool":true},{"option":"Erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR)","bool":false},{"option":"Fine needle aspiration (FNA)","bool":false},{"option":"Chest X-ray (CXR)","bool":false}],"id":99},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A detective is searching for evidence at a crime scene when he encounters fingerprints on the doorknob. He takes the impressions for examination. Inspection reveals that the pattern resembles hairpin heads that are elongated in the left direction. What is the most likely fingerprint pattern in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Loop","bool":true},{"option":"Arch","bool":false},{"option":"Composite","bool":false},{"option":"Tented arch","bool":false},{"option":"Whorl","bool":false}],"id":100},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A young boy is arrested due to a criminal charge. The court orders for a detailed forensic examination to determine his age. Pelvic X-ray findings show that the ischium and pubis are not united. What is the approximate age of the boy?","answers":[{"option":"25 years or more","bool":false},{"option":"Less than 25 years","bool":false},{"option":"Less than 7 years","bool":true},{"option":"Less than 12 years","bool":false},{"option":"Less than 18 years","bool":false}],"id":101},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 21-year-old female presents with petechiae on her skin and episodes of epistaxis for the last two months. On examination, there is no hepatosplenomegaly or lymphadenopathy. Which of the following is the most sensitive earliest test for making a diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Bone marrow aspiration","bool":false},{"option":"Antinuclear antibody (ANA) profile","bool":false},{"option":"Liver function test","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet count","bool":true},{"option":"Reticulocyte count","bool":false}],"id":102},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A person undergoes ileal resection. After some days he develops weakness, shortness of breath, and anemia. Which anemia can it possibly be?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic blood loss anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":true}],"id":103},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which interleukin is required for the growth and proliferation of all the stem cells?","answers":[{"option":"Interleukin-2","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-5","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-4","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-1","bool":false},{"option":"Interleukin-3","bool":true}],"id":104},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 30-year-old man presents with a history of hematuria for 15 days. He also had an episode of gum bleed one day back. Considering idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP) as the diagnosis, which of the following is the best initial treatment of choice?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombopoietin agonist","bool":false},{"option":"Corticosteroids","bool":true},{"option":"Danazole","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmapheresis","bool":false},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":false}],"id":105},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 50-year-old female who has recently been diagnosed with hypertension presents to the clinic for a routine follow-up examination. On workup, she has abnormal values of hemoglobin (Hb) 7.4 mg/dl, MCV 84 fl, creatinine 5.4 mg/dl, blood urea nitrogen (BUN) 65 mmol/L, potassium 5.2 mEq/L, sodium 130 mEq/L, phosphorus 5.0 mEq/L, calcium 6.7 mg/dl. Which of the following is the most likely cause of decreased Hb in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"B12 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Drug-induced gastritis","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Deficiency of erythropoietin","bool":true},{"option":"Folic acid deficiency","bool":false}],"id":106},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 16-year-old boy presents to the emergency department with the complaint of swelling of the right knee joint after trivial trauma. History is significant for similar incidences over the past 4 years. Their family history is positive for a bleeding disorder. Investigations show: hemoglobin -  10 g/dL, white cell count - 5,000/uL, platelets - 200,000/uL, factor VIII - normal, prothrombin time (PT) - 16 seconds (control - 14 seconds), activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT) - 48 seconds (control - 35 seconds). Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":true},{"option":"Acquired hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Von willebrand disease","bool":false}],"id":107},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"In case of an injury, a deficiency of which of the following would impair the adhesion of platelets to the subendothelial collagen?","answers":[{"option":"Antithrombin III","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand factor","bool":true},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinogen stabilizing factor","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmin","bool":false}],"id":108},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Where will hypostasis be seen in a body drowned in running water?","answers":[{"option":"No lividity will be seen","bool":true},{"option":"Front of the nose","bool":false},{"option":"Dependant part of upper limbs","bool":false},{"option":"Lower limbs","bool":false},{"option":"Back of the body","bool":false}],"id":109},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following genotypes correctly correspond to the silent carrier state of alpha thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"α α/α –","bool":true},{"option":"α –/α –","bool":false},{"option":"αα/αα","bool":false},{"option":"α α/– –","bool":false},{"option":"– –/– α","bool":false}],"id":110},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A dead body is brought to the mortuary for post mortem examination. The post-mortem rigidity is present throughout the body from head to toe. What is the estimated time of death?","answers":[{"option":"12-24 hours","bool":true},{"option":"4-18 hours","bool":false},{"option":"2-4 hours","bool":false},{"option":"24-36 hours","bool":false},{"option":"36-48 hours","bool":false}],"id":111},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A dead body is brought in for post mortem examination and according to an eye witness, the death occurred 6-8 hours ago. Which of these signs will confirm the witness's account?","answers":[{"option":"Fully developed but fixed lividity","bool":true},{"option":"Rigor mortis in the entire body","bool":false},{"option":"Blister development under the skin","bool":false},{"option":"Greenish discoloration of the right flank","bool":false},{"option":"Fully developed but not fixed lividity","bool":false}],"id":112},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which transfusion product of blood carries the highest risk of bacterial contamination?","answers":[{"option":"Cryoprecipitate","bool":false},{"option":"Whole blood","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Packed red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":true}],"id":113},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following white blood cells produce the major basic protein?","answers":[{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false}],"id":114},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"The age of a young boy needs to be determined. Dental X-ray reveals mixed dentition and an examination of the oral cavity reveals that the first and second molars have erupted. What is the approximate age of this boy?","answers":[{"option":"10 years","bool":false},{"option":"12 to 13 years","bool":true},{"option":"6 to 7 years","bool":false},{"option":"10 to 12 years","bool":false},{"option":"8 to 9 years","bool":false}],"id":115},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which one of the following is not one of the reasons why oral iron gluconate is not preferred?","answers":[{"option":"Metallic taste","bool":true},{"option":"Upset GIT","bool":false},{"option":"Black stools","bool":false},{"option":"Abdominal pain","bool":false},{"option":"Vomiting","bool":false}],"id":116},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 32-year-old woman has given birth to a stillborn hydropic baby with hepatosplenomegaly. What will be seen in her hemoglobin electrophoresis?","answers":[{"option":"HbF","bool":false},{"option":"HbH","bool":false},{"option":"HbS","bool":false},{"option":"Hb Barts","bool":true},{"option":"HbA2","bool":false}],"id":117},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A body is recovered from a densely populated neighborhood. The body is in an advanced stage of putrefaction, with greenish discoloration of the skin, distention of the abdomen, and muscle rigidity. Which of the following is the cause of rigidity in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Heat stiffening","bool":false},{"option":"Instantaneous rigor","bool":false},{"option":"Cold stiffening","bool":false},{"option":"Rigor mortis","bool":false},{"option":"Gas stiffening","bool":true}],"id":118},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A girl is brought to the outpatient department with complaints of gum bleeding, and epistaxis. Her complete blood count (CBC) shows a normal platelet count and prolonged bleeding time. There is a family history of a younger sister with easy bruising. What is the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":true},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":false},{"option":"Drug induced thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K deficiency","bool":false}],"id":119},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"Which one of these disorders are characterized by the presence of 'smudge cells' in the peripheral smear?","answers":[{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Myeloproliferative neoplasms","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myeloblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":true}],"id":120},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 70-year-old man has experienced increasing fatigue for the past 6 months. On physical examination, he has non-tender axillary and cervical lymphadenopathy but no hepatosplenomegaly. The CBC shows hemoglobin, 9.5 g/dL; hematocrit, 28%; MCV, 90 μm3; platelet count, 120,000/mm3; and WBC count, 42,000/mm3. His peripheral blood smear shows a monotonous population of small, round, mature-looking lymphocytes. Flow cytometry shows these cells as CD19+, CD5+, CD23-, and deoxynucleotidyl transferase negative (TdT−). Cytogenetic and molecular analysis of the abnormal cells in his blood will most likely reveal which of the following alterations?","answers":[{"option":"t(9;22) leading to BCR-ABL rearrangement","bool":false},{"option":"t(14;18) leading to BCL2 overexpression","bool":false},{"option":"t(8;14) leading to c-MYC overexpression","bool":false},{"option":"Clonal rearrangement of T-cell receptor genes","bool":false},{"option":"Clonal rearrangement of immunoglobulin genes","bool":true}],"id":121},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What does corpus delicti mean?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Corpse that is pleasant to the taste","bool":false},{"option":"Body that is found at scene of crime","bool":false},{"option":"Proof that a crime has been committed","bool":true},{"option":"Proof of guilt of crime","bool":false}],"id":122},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the below-enlisted ranges best represent the mixed dentition period?","answers":[{"option":"7-12","bool":false},{"option":"6-10","bool":false},{"option":"6-12","bool":true},{"option":"6-14","bool":false},{"option":"7-10","bool":false}],"id":123},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is true regarding Gustafson's method of age estimation?","answers":[{"option":"Provides the most accurate estimate of age","bool":false},{"option":"Makes use of incremental lines to estimate age","bool":false},{"option":"Consists of macroscopic examination of the tooth","bool":false},{"option":"Helps in age estimation between 25-60 years","bool":true},{"option":"Relies on the degree of calcification to estimate age","bool":false}],"id":124},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What do red blood cells look like in hereditary spherocytosis?","answers":[{"option":"Bite cells","bool":false},{"option":"Macrocytic","bool":false},{"option":"Target cells","bool":false},{"option":"Microcytic","bool":false},{"option":"Normocytic","bool":true}],"id":125},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following defines beta thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Reduced delta globin chain synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced zeta globin chain synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced alpha globin chain synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced gamma globin chain synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced beta globin chain synthesis","bool":true}],"id":126},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"How to check for Rh-sensitization in an Rh negative mother?","answers":[{"option":"Do amniocentesis","bool":false},{"option":"Do indirect Coombs test of the mother","bool":true},{"option":"Check antibody titers","bool":false},{"option":"Check blood group of father","bool":false},{"option":"Do direct Coomb's test of the mother","bool":false}],"id":127},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following occurs in leukoerythroblastosis?","answers":[{"option":"Presence of increased leukocytes in blood","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of increased red blood cells in blood","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of immature myeloid cells in blood","bool":true},{"option":"Presence of increased lymphocytes in blood","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of increased neutrophils in blood","bool":false}],"id":128},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"The majority of the type of Hemoglobin in alpha thalassemia with 4 allele deletions is:","answers":[{"option":"Beta-globin","bool":false},{"option":"Delta-globin","bool":false},{"option":"Gamma-globin","bool":true},{"option":"None of the above","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha-globin","bool":false}],"id":129},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Vaccination against which of the following microbial agents was added most recently to the Expanded Programme on Immunization (EPI) in Pakistan?","answers":[{"option":"Mumps","bool":false},{"option":"Diphtheria","bool":false},{"option":"Smallpox","bool":false},{"option":"Rotavirus","bool":true},{"option":"Human immunodeficiency virus","bool":false}],"id":130},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What is not a feature of platelet disorders?","answers":[{"option":"Ecchymoses","bool":false},{"option":"Immediate bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Mucosal bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Petechiae","bool":false}],"id":131},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is not due to a functional disorder of the platelets?","answers":[{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet pool deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Gray platelet syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Bernard-Soulier syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP)","bool":true}],"id":132},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Where does the defect lie in sickle cell disease?","answers":[{"option":"Ankyrin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin structure","bool":true},{"option":"Protoporphyrin synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Erythropoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"DNA","bool":false}],"id":133},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What is the most common manifestation of von Willebrand disease?","answers":[{"option":"Joint bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebral haemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Rectal bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Meningeal bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Gum bleeding","bool":true}],"id":134},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following vaccines is given intradermally in the right deltoid?","answers":[{"option":"MMR","bool":false},{"option":"Polio","bool":false},{"option":"Pentavaccine","bool":false},{"option":"BCG","bool":true},{"option":"Rotavirus","bool":false}],"id":135},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common type of mutation seen in β+ thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Gene deletion","bool":false},{"option":"Translocation","bool":false},{"option":"Splicing mutation","bool":true},{"option":"Chain terminator mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Promoter region mutation","bool":false}],"id":136},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"The Bacille Calmette-Guerin vaccine is administered via which route?","answers":[{"option":"Intramuscular","bool":false},{"option":"Subcutaneous","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous","bool":false},{"option":"Intradermal","bool":true},{"option":"Sublingual","bool":false}],"id":137},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is a feature seen in the whorl pattern of fingerprints?","answers":[{"option":"All of these are features","bool":true},{"option":"Central core","bool":false},{"option":"Two deltas which fall in the same straight plane","bool":false},{"option":"Intersecting ridges","bool":false},{"option":"More intricate than arch or loop pattern","bool":false}],"id":138},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What is used to measure the stored form of iron?","answers":[{"option":"Serum ferritin","bool":true},{"option":"Serum iron","bool":false},{"option":"Serum transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Serum albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Total iron binding capacity","bool":false}],"id":139},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What is thrombocytopenia defined as?","answers":[{"option":"Low megakaryocyte count","bool":false},{"option":"High platelet count","bool":false},{"option":"Low leukocyte count","bool":false},{"option":"Low platelet count","bool":true},{"option":"Low neutrophil count","bool":false}],"id":140},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which medical condition is not associated with venous thrombosis?","answers":[{"option":"Heart attack","bool":false},{"option":"Guillain-Barre syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Inflammatory bowel disease","bool":false},{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Pneumonia","bool":false}],"id":141},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What is the most common cause of vitamin B12 deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Ileal resection","bool":false},{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Diphyllobothrium","bool":false},{"option":"Gastrointestinal TB","bool":false},{"option":"Veganism","bool":false}],"id":142},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which test is conducted to determine the cause of deficiency of vitamin B12?","answers":[{"option":"Serum methylmalonic acid level","bool":false},{"option":"Coombs test","bool":false},{"option":"Schilling test","bool":true},{"option":"Serum vitamin B12 levels","bool":false},{"option":"Serum homocysteine level","bool":false}],"id":143},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"When do thalassemia major symptoms begin to appear?","answers":[{"option":"Within the first 2 years of life","bool":true},{"option":"Within the first 3 years of life","bool":false},{"option":"Within the last trimester","bool":false},{"option":"Within the first 4 years of life","bool":false},{"option":"In Intrauterine life","bool":false}],"id":144},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common cause of chronic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Folic acid deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hematopoietic growth factor deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Deficiency of trace elements","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":false}],"id":145},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following cells will be found in a peripheral blood film consistent with vitamin B12 deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Spherocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Schistocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Hypersegmented neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"None of the above","bool":false},{"option":"Burr cells","bool":false}],"id":146},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What of the following substances are found in mast cell granules?","answers":[{"option":"Bradykinin and mucus","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine and bradykinin","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine and heparin","bool":true},{"option":"Histamine and mucus","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin and mucus","bool":false}],"id":147},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Smudge cells are characteristic of which neoplastic condition?","answers":[{"option":"T-cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL)","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL)","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML)","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia (AML)","bool":false}],"id":148},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What is the most common cause of disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) in hospitalized patients?","answers":[{"option":"Amniotic fluid embolism","bool":false},{"option":"Cardiogenic shock","bool":false},{"option":"Acute respiratory distress syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Sepsis","bool":true},{"option":"Trauma","bool":false}],"id":149},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is not a cause of lymphocytosis?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Corticosteroids","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Post-splenectomy state","bool":false},{"option":"Bordetella pertussis infection","bool":false}],"id":150},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"A 45-year-old man recently had a gastrectomy. He now presents with lethargy, weakness and parasthesia of the limbs. His MCV is 110 fL. What is the likely cause of his symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Malabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Somatic neuropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid deficiency","bool":false}],"id":151},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"When is the second dose of the measles vaccine given?","answers":[{"option":"At 24 months","bool":false},{"option":"At 6 months","bool":false},{"option":"At birth","bool":false},{"option":"At 15 months","bool":true},{"option":"At 9 months","bool":false}],"id":152},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"How many vaccines are included in the expanded program on immunization (EPI)?","answers":[{"option":"7","bool":false},{"option":"15","bool":false},{"option":"3","bool":false},{"option":"10","bool":true},{"option":"9","bool":false}],"id":153},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"By what route is the measles vaccine given through?","answers":[{"option":"Intramuscular route","bool":false},{"option":"Oral route","bool":false},{"option":"Intadermal route","bool":false},{"option":"Intranasal route","bool":false},{"option":"Subcutaneous route","bool":true}],"id":154},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is not an inhibitor of platelet aggregation?","answers":[{"option":"Dipyridamole","bool":false},{"option":"Acetaminophen","bool":true},{"option":"Abciximab","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false}],"id":155},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What is the mode of action of corticosteroids?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibition of MCH-II","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of NF-κB in leukocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Inhibition of the IL-2 receptor","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of nitric oxide","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of macrophages","bool":false}],"id":156},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following conditions is most likely to cause extravascular hemolysis?","answers":[{"option":"RBCs have less hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"RBCs have nucleur remnants","bool":false},{"option":"RBCs are less deformable","bool":true},{"option":"RBCs are more deformable","bool":false},{"option":"RBCs are spherical","bool":false}],"id":157},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is not a subtype of classic Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocyte depleted","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocyte rich","bool":false},{"option":"Follicular","bool":true},{"option":"Mixed cellularity","bool":false},{"option":"Nodular sclerosis","bool":false}],"id":158},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following factors will cause sickling in sickle cell disease?","answers":[{"option":"Dehydration","bool":true},{"option":"Alcohol","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-malarials","bool":false},{"option":"Fava beans","bool":false},{"option":"Alkalosis","bool":false}],"id":159},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What characteristic cells are seen in Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Teardrop cells","bool":false},{"option":"Smudge cells","bool":false},{"option":"Target cells","bool":false},{"option":"Reed-Sternberg cells","bool":true},{"option":"Sezary cells","bool":false}],"id":160},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What mutation is the most common cause of acute promyelocytic leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"t(14;18)","bool":false},{"option":"t(15;17)","bool":true},{"option":"t(8;14)","bool":false},{"option":"t(11;18)","bool":false},{"option":"t(9;22)","bool":false}],"id":161},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following does NOT predispose an individual to warm autoimmune hemolytic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Alpha-methyldopa","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":false},{"option":"Mycoplasma infection","bool":true},{"option":"Quinidine","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":false}],"id":162},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"BCR-ABL mutation is seen in which leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic myelogenous leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myelogenous leukemia","bool":false}],"id":163},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"What is the main clinical finding in coagulation factor deficiencies?","answers":[{"option":"Eccyhmoses","bool":false},{"option":"Increased bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Pruritis","bool":false},{"option":"Petechiae","bool":false},{"option":"Slow capillary refill","bool":false}],"id":164},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"When does relative polycythemia occur?","answers":[{"option":"Dehydration","bool":true},{"option":"Eryhtropoetin producing malignancy","bool":false},{"option":"Exogenous erythropoetin","bool":false},{"option":"Under the sea","bool":false},{"option":"High altitude","bool":false}],"id":165},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Intrinsic coagulation is initiated by what factor?","answers":[{"option":"Hageman factor","bool":true},{"option":"Factor II","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin-like factor","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII","bool":false},{"option":"Rheumatoid factor","bool":false}],"id":166},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which type of cells are most commonly associated with chronic lymphocytic leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"Teardrop cells","bool":false},{"option":"Schistocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Smudge cells","bool":true},{"option":"Burr cells","bool":false},{"option":"Target cells","bool":false}],"id":167},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Hemoglobinuria during blood transfusion is due to transfusion of which of the following cells?","answers":[{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":true},{"option":"B-cells","bool":false},{"option":"T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma","bool":false}],"id":168},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Red blood cells in sickle cell disease are of what characteristic shape?","answers":[{"option":"Crescent-shaped","bool":true},{"option":"Rod-shaped","bool":false},{"option":"Helmet-shaped","bool":false},{"option":"Teardrop-shaped","bool":false},{"option":"Egg-shaped","bool":false}],"id":169},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"A 21-year-old male presented to the outpatient department with the complaints of shortness of breath, palor and increasing tiredness. On further evaluation he is found to follow a strict vegetarian diet. His laboratory reports show decreased haemoglobin, normal MCHC and MCV of 105 fL. What is most likely the cause of his symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin K deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin B6 deficency","bool":false},{"option":"Folate deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":false}],"id":170},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following statement about von Willebrand disease is true?","answers":[{"option":"Type 2 disease is more common and is qualitative","bool":false},{"option":"Type 1 is more common and is qualitative","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease has more episodes of bleeding than haemophilia.","bool":false},{"option":"There is decreased Von Willebrand factor with increased factor VIII levels.","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VIII levels are decreased","bool":true}],"id":171},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following statement is true about idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura?","answers":[{"option":"People above the age sixty should undergo screening for diffuse large B cell lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"A count less than 50,000 is associated with spontaneous bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"There is no need to check for human immunodeficiency virus","bool":false},{"option":"Disease severity cannot be predicted by the degree of thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"This disease is more common in males","bool":false}],"id":172},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following statement about polycythemia rubra vera is true?","answers":[{"option":"Headache, dizziness and tinnitus are common complaints.","bool":true},{"option":"It occurs in patients before the age of 40","bool":false},{"option":"It is not associated with peptic ulcer disease.","bool":false},{"option":"Less than 40% of the patients have  JAK-2 V617F mutationn.","bool":false},{"option":"Venesection rarely  gives prompt relief of hyperviscosity symptoms in this disease.","bool":false}],"id":173},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"A 27-year-old female presented to the outpatient department with complaints of anemia and also complains of dark-colored urine in the morning. Which of the following is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Paroxysmal nocturnal  haemoglobinuria","bool":true},{"option":"G6DP deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic cold haemagglutinin disease","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythaemia","bool":false}],"id":174},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"A histopathologist examines a blood film under his microscope which shows small lymphocytes with irregular borders. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute promyelocytic leukaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":true}],"id":175},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is not a feature of thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura?","answers":[{"option":"thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Central nervous system involvement","bool":false},{"option":"Raised prothrombin time and activated partial thromboplastin time","bool":true},{"option":"Fever","bool":false},{"option":"Renal failure","bool":false}],"id":176},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is true about disseminated intravascular coagulation?","answers":[{"option":"Prothrombin and activated partial thromboplastin time do not aid in diagnosis and prognosis","bool":false},{"option":"It is always associated with an underlying infection","bool":false},{"option":"Tranexamic acid is the mainstray of treatment","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin cannot be given","bool":false},{"option":"It can worsen many conditions such as septicemia etc","bool":true}],"id":177},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"A patient's reports show prolonged bleeding time but normal  prothrombin time (PT) and normal activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT). Which defect does the patient most likely have?","answers":[{"option":"Dysfibrinogenaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Deficiency of factors VII,\tX, V,\tprothrombin and fibrinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Deficiency of factors XII, XI, IX, VIII,\t X and V.","bool":false},{"option":"Disorder of platelet function","bool":true},{"option":"Fibrinogen deficiency","bool":false}],"id":178},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following statement about paraproteinaemias is true?","answers":[{"option":"It is polyclonal in association with multiple myeloma.","bool":false},{"option":"Paraproteinaemias have no association with rheumatoid arthritis or polymyalgia rheumatica.","bool":false},{"option":"Both  monoclonal and polyclonal immunoglobulins are produced.","bool":false},{"option":"It refers to over-production of one or more classes of immunoglobulin.","bool":true},{"option":"It is monoclonal in association with sarcoidosis.","bool":false}],"id":179},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"A patient came to the outpatient department with the complaints of anemia and lumbar tenderness. His lab reports show Calcium=12 mg/dl, Na=134mmol/L, K=4mmol/L, ESR=100 mm/hr and creatinine=4.8 mg/dl. The doctor suspects multiple myeloma. What should be the initial management?","answers":[{"option":"Non steroidal anti inflammatory drugs","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclophosphamide","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrate the patient","bool":true},{"option":"Blood transfusion","bool":false},{"option":"Steroids","bool":false}],"id":180},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is the most appropriate statement about haematopoietic stem cell transplantation?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia is a contradiction to stem cell transplantation.","bool":false},{"option":"Haematopoietic stem cell transplantation comes with considerably less morbidity and mortality.","bool":false},{"option":"Infertility is an early complication of stem cell transplantation.","bool":false},{"option":"In allogenic transplantation stem cells are taken from the patient.","bool":false},{"option":"The best results are found in patients with minimal residual disease who are less than 20 years of age who have a HLA-identical sibling donor.","bool":true}],"id":181},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"Which of the following statements is incorrect about deep venous thrombosis (DVT) in pregnancy?","answers":[{"option":"Lower molecular weight heparin (LMWH) is given as treatment","bool":false},{"option":"Diagnosed by doppler ultrasound","bool":false},{"option":"Usually unilateral","bool":false},{"option":"Women with a previous history of venous thromboembolism (VTE) who are receiving warfarin or other oral anticoagulants as prophylaxis should have these stopped prior to conception","bool":false},{"option":"Measurement of D-dimer levels is used in diagnosis","bool":true}],"id":182},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"An old man was rushed to the emergency department with hemoglobin levels of less than 6 mg/dl. His blood type isn’t available. Which blood type can be transfused to him in order to save his life?","answers":[{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"O negative","bool":true},{"option":"AB negative","bool":false},{"option":"O positive","bool":false},{"option":"AB positive","bool":false}],"id":183},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"A young female patient came to the clinic with primary amenorrhea and knee haemarthrosis. Her brother is a known case of haemophilia. What is the karyotype of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"XXY mosaicism","bool":false},{"option":"XXY","bool":false},{"option":"XO","bool":true},{"option":"XY","bool":false},{"option":"XX","bool":false}],"id":184},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2017"],"question":"An African patient came to the clinic with a history of multiple blood transfusions in the past. Which disease is he most likely suffering from?","answers":[{"option":"Beta thalassemia Major","bool":true},{"option":"Hereditary elliptocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Beta thalassemia intermedia","bool":false},{"option":"Haemoglobin H disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrops fetalis","bool":false}],"id":185},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Vitamin K is given as an antidote to warfarin therapy. How long do clotting factors take to return to their normal levels after the administration of vitamin K?","answers":[{"option":"6 minutes","bool":false},{"option":"6 days","bool":false},{"option":"6 hours","bool":false},{"option":"24 hours","bool":true},{"option":"48 hours","bool":false}],"id":186},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which drug acts as an inhibitor of the IL-2 receptor?","answers":[{"option":"Rapamycin","bool":false},{"option":"Cetuximab","bool":false},{"option":"Abciximab","bool":false},{"option":"Basiliximab","bool":true},{"option":"Bevacizumab","bool":false}],"id":187},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A patient undergoing treatment with heparin suddenly develops heparin-induced thrombocytopenia (HIT). Which of the following routes of management should be used to treat the patient?","answers":[{"option":"Cryoprecipitate or factor VIII","bool":false},{"option":"Desmopressin and tranexamic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Bivalirudin and dabigatran infusion","bool":true},{"option":"Continue heparin therapy","bool":false},{"option":"Apixaban infusion","bool":false}],"id":188},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following disorders can result in hydrops fetalis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemoglobin H disease","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha-thalassemia minor","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-thalassemia minor","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-thalassemia major","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin Barts disease","bool":true}],"id":189},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following should not be used in the treatment of disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)?","answers":[{"option":"Antifibrinolytics","bool":true},{"option":"Cryoprecipitate","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false}],"id":190},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Under section 361 PPC, kidnapping consists of taking a minor from his/her lawful guardian without the consent of the guardian. What is the age of cut-off?","answers":[{"option":"14 years if male and 16 years if female","bool":true},{"option":"14 years for both male and female","bool":false},{"option":"16 years for both male and female","bool":false},{"option":"16 years if male and 18 years if female","bool":false},{"option":"18 years if female and 16 years if male","bool":false}],"id":191},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"What percentage of the population needs to be immune to develop herd immunity against measles?","answers":[{"option":"90%","bool":false},{"option":"95%","bool":true},{"option":"75%","bool":false},{"option":"50%","bool":false},{"option":"85%","bool":false}],"id":192},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"During the medicolegal autopsy of a man who died in a house fire, it is noted that the sphenoparietal suture in the skull is closed. What is the approximate age of this body at the time of death?","answers":[{"option":"60 years","bool":false},{"option":"35 years","bool":false},{"option":"50 years","bool":false},{"option":"70 years","bool":true},{"option":"40 years","bool":false}],"id":193},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which joint is most commonly checked via X-ray to check bone age for precocious puberty?","answers":[{"option":"Shoulder","bool":false},{"option":"Knee","bool":false},{"option":"Wrist","bool":true},{"option":"Ankle","bool":false},{"option":"Hip","bool":false}],"id":194},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following diseases is correctly paired with their characteristic marker?","answers":[{"option":"G6PD - Heinz bodies","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell disease - target cells","bool":false},{"option":"Myelofibrosis - spherocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency - tear drop cells","bool":false},{"option":"Pyruvate kinase deficiency - hemoglobin crystals in RBCs","bool":false}],"id":195},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following substances is a strong activator of macrophage?","answers":[{"option":"IL-10","bool":false},{"option":"IL-4","bool":false},{"option":"Interferon-gamma","bool":true},{"option":"Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF)","bool":false},{"option":"Tumor growth factor (TGF)","bool":false}],"id":196},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A 4-year-old boy is brought to the emergency room with a painful swollen right knee. The parents give a history of mild trauma, with the child falling from standing height. The knee is visibly swollen, bluish in color and movement is restricted due to pain. The parents also report a history of prolonged bleeding following his circumcision. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Septic arthritis","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Bernard-Soulier syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Essential thrombocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":true}],"id":197},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is not an adverse effect of transfusion?","answers":[{"option":"Anaphylaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Febrile reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Delayed hemolytic reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Acute hemolytic reaction","bool":false}],"id":198},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Sideroblastic anemia is NOT associated with which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin B6 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Alcohol poisoning","bool":false},{"option":"TB patient undergoing isoniazid therapy","bool":false},{"option":"Copper deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":true}],"id":199},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A blood film shows hypochromic and microcytic red blood cells with poikilocytosis. What is the diagnosis based on this appearance?","answers":[{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":200},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"What is the most common cause of generalized lymphadenopathy?","answers":[{"option":"Fungal infection","bool":false},{"option":"Drug hypersensitivity","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":false},{"option":"Viral infection","bool":true},{"option":"Sarcoidosis","bool":false}],"id":201},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Vitamin B12 deficiency is associated with which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Microcytic hypochromic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell disease","bool":false},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":202},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"When is the measles-1 vaccine administered?","answers":[{"option":"9 months","bool":true},{"option":"At birth","bool":false},{"option":"12 months","bool":false},{"option":"10 weeks","bool":false},{"option":"14 weeks","bool":false}],"id":203},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Spread to the testicles and central nervous system is characteristic of which of the following neoplasias?","answers":[{"option":"Mantle cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Burkitt lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myelogenous leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":false}],"id":204},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A patient complains of repeated instances of intense itching after a hot shower. Which condition is responsible for this?","answers":[{"option":"Myelofibrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Essential thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia vera","bool":true},{"option":"Burkitt lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":205},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following shows intravascular hemolysis?","answers":[{"option":"Warm immune hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary elliptocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell disease","bool":false},{"option":"Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria","bool":true},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false}],"id":206},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Phenytoin decreases the action of warfarin by which of the following mechanisms?","answers":[{"option":"Increases renal clearance","bool":false},{"option":"Displaces warfarin from plasma proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Enhances warfarin metabolism","bool":true},{"option":"Inhibits intestinal absorption","bool":false},{"option":"Increases clotting factor synthesis","bool":false}],"id":207},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is not true for leukemoid reaction?","answers":[{"option":"May involve neutrophils, eosinophils and lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Absolute leukocyte count usually exceeds 25,000/mm3","bool":false},{"option":"It is very similar to chronic myelogenous leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Normal bone marrow response to cytokines released by cells in infection","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocyte alkaline phosphatase (LAP) score is decreased","bool":true}],"id":208},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Monocytosis is seen in which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Sterile inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Pemphigus","bool":false},{"option":"Bordetella pertussis","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberculosis","bool":true},{"option":"Vasculitis","bool":false}],"id":209},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"On palpation, the supraclavicular lymph nodes of a 50-year-old man feel stony hard. Which of the following is the most likely underlying cause?","answers":[{"option":"Tuberculosis","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Infection","bool":false},{"option":"Inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Malignancy","bool":true}],"id":210},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"What is the literal translation of the legal term 'corpus delicti'?","answers":[{"option":"Weapon of choice","bool":false},{"option":"The will of the deceased","bool":false},{"option":"Reason of the murder","bool":false},{"option":"Body of the crime","bool":true},{"option":"Degree of the crime","bool":false}],"id":211},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A 75-year-old man presents to the hospital with generalized painless lymphadenopathy. Laboratory findings reveal a white blood cell count of 20,000 cells/mm³. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Myelofibrosis","bool":false}],"id":212},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A 7-year-old child presents to the outpatient department with his mother, with complaints of weight loss, fever, pallor, and bleeding over the body for three weeks. On examination, there is generalized lymphadenopathy with hepatosplenomegaly. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false}],"id":213},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following causes extravascular hemolysis?","answers":[{"option":"Mechanical injury","bool":false},{"option":"Complement fixation","bool":false},{"option":"Falciparum malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Exogenous toxic factor","bool":false},{"option":"When red blood cells become less deformable","bool":true}],"id":214},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following agents is used in the treatment of vitamin B12 deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Hydroxycobalamin","bool":true},{"option":"Folate","bool":false},{"option":"Methylcobalamin","bool":false},{"option":"Menadione","bool":false},{"option":"Retinol","bool":false}],"id":215},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is the cause of atypical hemolytic uremic syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Decreased levels of ADAMTS13","bool":false},{"option":"Complement factor H deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE)","bool":false},{"option":"Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)","bool":false},{"option":"Escherichia coli (E. coli)","bool":false}],"id":216},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Tetanus exotoxin treated with formalin is an example of which type of vaccine?","answers":[{"option":"Toxoid vaccine","bool":true},{"option":"Killed vaccine","bool":false},{"option":"Subunit vaccine","bool":false},{"option":"Polysaccharide vaccine","bool":false},{"option":"Live attenuated vaccine","bool":false}],"id":217},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is an example of live attenuated vaccine?","answers":[{"option":"Measles","bool":true},{"option":"Cholera","bool":false},{"option":"Diphtheria","bool":false},{"option":"Pertussis","bool":false},{"option":"Rabies","bool":false}],"id":218},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"What is the most likely gastrointestinal manifestation of acute graft-versus-host disease (GVHD)?","answers":[{"option":"Constipation","bool":false},{"option":"Dysphagia","bool":false},{"option":"Vomiting","bool":false},{"option":"Diarrhea","bool":true},{"option":"Jaundice","bool":false}],"id":219},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Why are patients with polycythemia vera predisposed to thrombotic events?","answers":[{"option":"Endothelial damage","bool":false},{"option":"Hypercoagulability","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperviscosity of blood","bool":true},{"option":"Stasis","bool":false},{"option":"Vessel congestion","bool":false}],"id":220},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"BCR-ABL fusion gene product is seen in which of the following leukemias?","answers":[{"option":"T-cell leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myelogenous leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia","bool":false}],"id":221},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"The activation of the extrinsic coagulation system occurs with the release of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Tissue thromboplastin","bool":true},{"option":"Adenosine diphosphate (ADP)","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand factor (vWF)","bool":false},{"option":"High-molecular-weight kininogen","bool":false},{"option":"Subendothelial collagen","bool":false}],"id":222},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is done to ensure that a research project has no errors?","answers":[{"option":"Devise a hypothesis","bool":false},{"option":"Conduct a pilot study","bool":true},{"option":"Select a sample size","bool":false},{"option":"Collect statistical data","bool":false},{"option":"Carry out a literature review","bool":false}],"id":223},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A 12-year-old boy presents to the clinic because he is passing cola-colored urine for 5 days. He was diagnosed with malaria 2 weeks ago and is taking chloroquine. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false}],"id":224},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following can reverse the toxic effects of heparin?","answers":[{"option":"Alkylating agent","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false},{"option":"Protamine sulfate","bool":true},{"option":"Low molecular weight heparin","bool":false}],"id":225},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is not a complication of a massive blood transfusion?","answers":[{"option":"Hyperkalemia","bool":false},{"option":"Congestive heart failure","bool":false},{"option":"Volume overload","bool":false},{"option":"Hypothermia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypercalcemia","bool":true}],"id":226},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A 35-year-old man presents to the clinic with easy fatigability and weakness. Spherocytes can be seen on peripheral blood smear. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false}],"id":227},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following would not cause intravascular hemolysis?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":true},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":false},{"option":"Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria","bool":false}],"id":228},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Which of the following conditions is associated with the Philadelphia chromosome?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Primary myelofibrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":false}],"id":229},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A 26-year-old male presents to the clinic with enlarged lymph nodes in the neck, night sweats, and unexplained weight loss over the past few months. He reports intermittent low-grade fever and generalized fatigue. A physical examination reveals painless, firm, rubbery lymph nodes in the cervical region. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Non-Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Tuberculosis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)","bool":false},{"option":"Sarcoidosis","bool":false}],"id":230},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"A 30-year-old male is brought to the emergency department after being bitten by a snake while hiking. He complains of severe pain and swelling at the site of the snakebite and a widespread rash all over his body. Laboratory tests reveal deranged prothrombin time (PT), activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT), and a low platelet count. What is the initial management of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Administer antivenom","bool":false},{"option":"Apply a tourniquet above the snakebite site","bool":false},{"option":"Administer pain relievers","bool":false},{"option":"Start antibiotics","bool":false},{"option":"Start intravenous fluids","bool":true}],"id":231},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2018"],"question":"Auer rods are typically seen in which type of hematological malignancy?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL)","bool":false},{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia (AML)","bool":true},{"option":"Non-Hodgkin lymphoma (NHL)","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple myeloma","bool":false}],"id":232},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Blister cells and bite cells are seen in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Pyruvate kinase deficiency","bool":false}],"id":233},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What type of anemia is caused by Diphyllobothrium latum (fish tapeworm)?","answers":[{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false}],"id":234},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"In which of the following conditions will non-neoplastic cells be seen?","answers":[{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple myeloma","bool":false},{"option":"Non-hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":false}],"id":235},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is the most common cause of iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Dietary deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Gastrectomy","bool":false},{"option":"Increased demand during puberty","bool":false},{"option":"Malabsorption syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Hookworm infestation","bool":false}],"id":236},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following nail abnormalities is observed in iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Koilonychia","bool":true},{"option":"Pitting","bool":false},{"option":"Splinter hemorrhages","bool":false},{"option":"Erythronychia","bool":false},{"option":"Paronychia","bool":false}],"id":237},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"For diagnosis of iron deficiency anemia, which one of the following features is seen in the blood film?","answers":[{"option":"Poikilocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Ringed sideroblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Target cells","bool":false},{"option":"Bite cells","bool":false},{"option":"Spherocytes","bool":false}],"id":238},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following is used to check for the morphology of red blood cells (RBCs)?","answers":[{"option":"Red cell distribution width (RDW)","bool":false},{"option":"Mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH)","bool":false},{"option":"Mean corpuscular hemoglobin concentration (MCHC)","bool":false},{"option":"Mean corpuscular volume (MCV)","bool":true},{"option":"Hematocrit","bool":false}],"id":239},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Platelet infusion is contraindicated in which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP)","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)","bool":false},{"option":"Ocular surgery","bool":false}],"id":240},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is the term used for the origin and synthesis of white blood cells (WBCs)?","answers":[{"option":"Hematopoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"Erythropoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"Granulocytopoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"Leukopoiesis","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombopoiesis","bool":false}],"id":241},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"In which one of the following conditions are Reed-Sternberg cells seen?","answers":[{"option":"Burkitt lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Mantle cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Non-Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":242},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following are long-lived phagocytic cells present abundantly in gastric tissue?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Dendritic cells","bool":false}],"id":243},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following cells will be increased in a parasitic reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false}],"id":244},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following patient factors is not important to note before a transfusion?","answers":[{"option":"Occupation","bool":true},{"option":"Date of birth","bool":false},{"option":"RhD group","bool":false},{"option":"Sex","bool":false},{"option":"Surname","bool":false}],"id":245},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which vaccines should be given at birth according to the expanded program on immunization (EPI) schedule?","answers":[{"option":"BCG","bool":false},{"option":"OPV-0","bool":false},{"option":"BCG + OPV-I","bool":false},{"option":"BCG + OPV-0 + Rotavirus-I","bool":false},{"option":"BCG + OPV-0 + hep B","bool":true}],"id":246},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following represents hot and cold antibodies respectively?","answers":[{"option":"IgD and IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgG and IgM","bool":true},{"option":"IgG and IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgM and IgE","bool":false},{"option":"IgA and IgE","bool":false}],"id":247},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 5-year-old child is brought to the emergency department with extreme pain in his hands and feet. Examination reveals dactylitis (swelling of bones), pulmonary infiltrates, and signs and symptoms of anemia. While giving history, the child's parents talk about an inherited disorder that runs in the family. Which condition is the child most likely to be suffering from?","answers":[{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell disease","bool":true},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP)","bool":false}],"id":248},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following is true about aplastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Hypercellular bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Patients do not require blood support","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatosplenomegaly is not present","bool":true},{"option":"It is not immune mediated","bool":false}],"id":249},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following is correct about mixed cellularity lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Does not involve abdominal lymph nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Reed-Sternberg cells are not present","bool":false},{"option":"High eosinophils count","bool":true},{"option":"Poor prognosis","bool":false},{"option":"Not caused by Epstein-Barr virus","bool":false}],"id":250},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 24-year-old man is brought to the emergency after a motorcycle accident. He is bleeding profusely from the wound on his leg. He has no previous medical or surgical history. When a blood smear is performed, what type of red blood cells are likely to be seen?","answers":[{"option":"Macrocytic hypochromic","bool":false},{"option":"Normocytic hypochromic","bool":false},{"option":"Normocytic normochromic","bool":true},{"option":"Microcytic hypochromic","bool":false},{"option":"Macrocytic hypochromic","bool":false}],"id":251},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 7-year-old African kid is brought to the clinic with a swelling around his jaw that has been slowly increasing in size over the past few months. Biopsy of the mass reveals a starry sky appearance. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Burkitt lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Mantle cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Follicular lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":252},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following statements is true for Hodgkin's lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Lacunar cells are not present","bool":false},{"option":"CD-15 and CD-30 markers are present","bool":true},{"option":"Absence of Reed Sternberg cells","bool":false},{"option":"No eosinophilia","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":253},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following conditions is most likely to show positive Coomb's test?","answers":[{"option":"Hodgkins lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":false}],"id":254},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 32-year-old female had to undergo a total gastrectomy. After almost 2 years, she started developing weakness, shortness of breath, occasional dizziness and difficulty in walking. She went to her doctor to get a check-up done. On examining her, the doctor noticed that she also had pale skin and yellowing of sclera. What would be the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Normocytic normochromic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Microcytic hypochromic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":false}],"id":255},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which pattern of serum protein electrophoresis is seen in multiple myeloma?","answers":[{"option":"Monoclonal band","bool":true},{"option":"Double peak","bool":false},{"option":"Polyclonal band","bool":false},{"option":"Diffuse band","bool":false},{"option":"Slumped band","bool":false}],"id":256},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following chromosomal translocations is found in chronic myelogenous leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"t(9;22)","bool":true},{"option":"t(4;14)","bool":false},{"option":"t(8;21)","bool":false},{"option":"t(15;17)","bool":false},{"option":"Trisomy 12q","bool":false}],"id":257},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is the term used for abnormal and uncontrolled production of white blood cells (WBCs)?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Leukopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Leukopoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphopenia","bool":false}],"id":258},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most abundant cell type in the blood?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Granulocyte","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false}],"id":259},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Intravascular hemolysis is one of the causes of hemolytic anemia. Which one of the following is not a feature of intravascular hemolysis?","answers":[{"option":"Raised haptoglobin","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Hemosiderinuria","bool":false},{"option":"Urobilinogen in urine","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobinemia","bool":false}],"id":260},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is most likely seen due to platelet disorders?","answers":[{"option":"Normal platelet count with raised PT and aPTT","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia with normal PT and aPTT","bool":true},{"option":"Normal platelet count with normal PT and aPTT","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia with raised PT but normal aPTT","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia with raised PT and aPTT","bool":false}],"id":261},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"The diagnosis of Hodgkin lymphoma depends on what histologic finding?","answers":[{"option":"Infiltrative eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Sezary cells","bool":false},{"option":"Pautrier microabscesses","bool":false},{"option":"Auer rods","bool":false},{"option":"Reed-Sternberg cells","bool":true}],"id":262},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which coagulation factor is deficient in hemophilia B?","answers":[{"option":"IX","bool":true},{"option":"V","bool":false},{"option":"XI","bool":false},{"option":"II","bool":false},{"option":"VIII","bool":false}],"id":263},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which vitamin deficiency can lead to a protein C deficiency?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin A","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin B","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin D","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin E","bool":false}],"id":264},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following types of immunity occurs when an individual is administered with an immunoglobulin made in another host?","answers":[{"option":"Artificial","bool":false},{"option":"Active","bool":false},{"option":"Innate","bool":false},{"option":"Natural","bool":false},{"option":"Passive","bool":true}],"id":265},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following conversions uses vitamin B12 as a co-factor?","answers":[{"option":"Serine to glycine","bool":false},{"option":"Succinyl CoA to succinate","bool":false},{"option":"Homocysteine to methionine","bool":true},{"option":"Pyruvate to acetyl coA","bool":false},{"option":"Oxaloacetate to citrate","bool":false}],"id":266},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following conditions is true about the leukemoid reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Response to an infection","bool":true},{"option":"Blood smear contains mature white blood cells and red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Only involves neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Always presents with abnormal bone marrow","bool":false}],"id":267},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is the movement of white blood cells in to the tissues in response to interleukins called?","answers":[{"option":"Clumping","bool":false},{"option":"Precipitation","bool":false},{"option":"Proliferation of lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Diapedesis","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotaxis","bool":true}],"id":268},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What type of vaccine is the diphtheria vaccine?","answers":[{"option":"Immunoglobulin","bool":false},{"option":"Subunit","bool":false},{"option":"Toxin","bool":false},{"option":"Live attenuated","bool":false},{"option":"Toxoid","bool":true}],"id":269},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"The erythropoietin receptor belongs to which class of receptors?","answers":[{"option":"Tyrosine kinase receptor","bool":false},{"option":"G protein-coupled receptor","bool":false},{"option":"Ligand-gated ion channel","bool":false},{"option":"Intracellular receptor","bool":false},{"option":"Cytokine receptor","bool":true}],"id":270},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase (TdT) is a marker for which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Mature B and T cells","bool":false},{"option":"Reed-Sternberg cells","bool":false},{"option":"NK cells and granulocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Germinal centre B cells","bool":false},{"option":"Pre-B and pre-T cells","bool":true}],"id":271},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"In sickle cell anemia, glutamate at the 6th position of the beta chain of hemoglobin is substituted by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Valine","bool":true},{"option":"Proline","bool":false},{"option":"Tyrosine","bool":false},{"option":"Lysine","bool":false},{"option":"Glycine","bool":false}],"id":272},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 24-year-old presents with bruises in the emergency department. Laboratory results showed normal bleeding time but prolonged prothrombin time (PT) and partial thromboplastin time (PTT). Which one of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"von Willebrand factor (VWF)","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Coagulation disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP)","bool":false}],"id":273},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following antibodies of the recipient is responsible for causing urticaria in the donor's blood?","answers":[{"option":"Ig G antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Ig A antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Ig D antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Ig M antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Ig E antibodies","bool":true}],"id":274},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 37-year-old woman presents to the outpatient department with a complaint of a lump in the right breast. The general physical examination concludes mass in the right upper quadrant of the breast and an enlarged right axial lymph node. She was diagnosed with Hodgkin lymphoma 7 years ago but was treated for it and completely cured. What is the most likely diagnosis of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Fibroadenoma","bool":false},{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Breast cancer","bool":true},{"option":"Non-Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":275},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is immunization to the whole community referred to as?","answers":[{"option":"Innate immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Herd immunity","bool":true},{"option":"Active immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Adaptive immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Passive immunity","bool":false}],"id":276},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following are non-neoplastic cells?","answers":[{"option":"Blast cells","bool":true},{"option":"Popcorn cells","bool":false},{"option":"Mononuclear cells","bool":false},{"option":"Lacunar cells","bool":false},{"option":"Reed Steerberg cells","bool":false}],"id":277},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is implicated in Hodgkin's disease?","answers":[{"option":"Skin","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Blood","bool":false}],"id":278},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which surgery most commonly causes deep vein thrombosis (DVT)?","answers":[{"option":"Cardiothoracic surgery","bool":false},{"option":"Coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG)","bool":false},{"option":"Hip surgery","bool":true},{"option":"Carpal tunnel surgery","bool":false},{"option":"Thyroid surgery","bool":false}],"id":279},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is the diagnostic test for deep vein thrombosis (DVT)?","answers":[{"option":"D-dimer test","bool":false},{"option":"Doppler ultrasound","bool":true},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)","bool":false},{"option":"Venography","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography (CT)","bool":false}],"id":280},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which drug should be given to a patient with deep vein thrombosis (DVT)?","answers":[{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Coumarin","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":true},{"option":"Alteplase","bool":false}],"id":281},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 24-year-old boy was brought to the emergency with a petechial hemorrhage with no fever. Upon examination, he had mild splenomegaly but no neurological symptoms. His laboratory results showed prolonged bleeding time but normal prothrombin time (PT) and partial thromboplastin time (PTT). Which one of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP)","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic-uremic syndrome (HUS)","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)","bool":false}],"id":282},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A patient presented with disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) due to sepsis by gram-negative bacteria in the emergency. Which one of the following is the first step for the management of DIC in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"IV antibiotic + IV hydration","bool":true},{"option":"Platelet","bool":false},{"option":"Whole blood","bool":false},{"option":"Cryoprecipitate","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false}],"id":283},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What antibody is found in antiphospholipid syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Anti-cyclic citrullinated peptide (anti-CCP) antibody","bool":false},{"option":"Rheumatoid factor (RF)","bool":false},{"option":"Antinuclear antibody (ANA)","bool":false},{"option":"Anticardiolipin antibody","bool":true},{"option":"Anti-double stranded DNA (Anti-dsDNA) antibody","bool":false}],"id":284},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A man has a history of eczema and allergic asthma. Which diagnostic test is performed?","answers":[{"option":"Urinalysis","bool":false},{"option":"Red blood cell sedimentation","bool":false},{"option":"Peripheral blood smear","bool":false},{"option":"Chest X-ray","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":true}],"id":285},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is most commonly not found among all types of myeloproliferative disorders?","answers":[{"option":"Hypocellular bone marrow","bool":true},{"option":"JAK 2 kinase mutation","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Hypercellular bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Involves myoblasts","bool":false}],"id":286},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements is true about acute myelogenous leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"Not caused due to alkylating agents or radiation","bool":false},{"option":"Gum infiltration","bool":true},{"option":"No association with Down syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Involves cyclin D1 mutation","bool":false}],"id":287},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following substances are released from granules in basophils?","answers":[{"option":"Histamine and heparin","bool":true},{"option":"vWF","bool":false},{"option":"ADP and calcium ions","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinogen and fibronectin","bool":false}],"id":288},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is observed in chronic myeloid leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"Eosinophilia with increased IgE","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cell degranulation","bool":false},{"option":"JAK 2 tyrosine kinase mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Tissue necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Basophilia","bool":true}],"id":289},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 65-year-old man presented to the clinic with complaints of severe backache. The doctor ordered laboratory tests that revealed a hemoglobin level of 7.0 mg/dL and serum creatinine of 2.0 mg/dL. Which of the following findings would also be included in the report?","answers":[{"option":"Hypercalcemia","bool":true},{"option":"Oxaluria","bool":false},{"option":"Hypocalcemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypernatremia","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperkalemia","bool":false}],"id":290},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following hemoglobins are present in thalassemia major?","answers":[{"option":"Normal HbA, increased HbA2 (2-8%)","bool":false},{"option":"Normal HbA, increased HbA2 and more than 90% HbF","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased HbA, raised HbA2 and HbF","bool":false},{"option":"Normal HbA and increased HbF","bool":false},{"option":"HbA absent, HbA2 normal or high or low, HbF markedly increased","bool":true}],"id":291},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 5-day-old baby born after a healthy, full-term pregnancy started bleeding into his genitals. His mother took anti-epileptic drugs throughout her pregnancy. What is the likely cause of the bleeding disorder in this infant?","answers":[{"option":"Alcohol abuse","bool":false},{"option":"Long-term phenobarbital","bool":true},{"option":"Congenital leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Poisoning","bool":false}],"id":292},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"In which one of the following scenarios is vitamin K given?","answers":[{"option":"Peptic ulcer","bool":false},{"option":"Worm infection","bool":false},{"option":"Obstructive jaundice","bool":true},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Colonic polyp","bool":false}],"id":293},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is donor blood screened for before a transfusion?","answers":[{"option":"Parasitic infection","bool":false},{"option":"Viral infection","bool":true},{"option":"Bacterial infection","bool":false},{"option":"Fungal infection","bool":false},{"option":"Protozoal infection","bool":false}],"id":294},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A pregnant woman in her 3rd trimester is diagnosed with iron deficiency anemia. Which of the following type of cells will be found on her blood smear?","answers":[{"option":"Hypochromic, Microcytic","bool":true},{"option":"Hypochromic, Normocytic","bool":false},{"option":"Hypochromic, Normocytic","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperchromic, Normocytic","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperchromic, Macrocytic","bool":false}],"id":295},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements about Hodgkin lymphoma is correct?","answers":[{"option":"Negative for CD15 and CD30","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Mixed cellularity is the most commonly found Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Painful enlargement of lymph nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of Reed sternberg cells","bool":true}],"id":296},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following lymphomas is involved in the Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) infection?","answers":[{"option":"Multiple myeloma","bool":false},{"option":"Burkitt lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Squamous cell carcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Kaposi's sarcoma","bool":false},{"option":"Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":297},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 5-month-old child presented with bleeding from the genitals. His maternal uncle had a history of prolonged bleeding. What will be the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":true},{"option":"von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin induced thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false}],"id":298},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements is true about tacrolimus?","answers":[{"option":"Stimulates T-cell activation","bool":false},{"option":"Calcineurin inhibitor","bool":true},{"option":"IL-2 transcription occurs","bool":false},{"option":"Does not bind to FK506 protein","bool":false},{"option":"Does not cause nephrotoxicity","bool":false}],"id":299},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"In which one of the following blue granules are most likely to be seen?","answers":[{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":true},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false}],"id":300},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following cells is present in acute inflammation?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":true},{"option":"T lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false}],"id":301},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is the most common cause of vitamin B12 deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Diphyllobothrium","bool":false},{"option":"Veganism","bool":false},{"option":"Gastrointestinal TB","bool":false},{"option":"Ileal resection","bool":false},{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":true}],"id":302},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 52-year-old patient presented to the clinic to get his blood reports examined. He was being investigated following his presentation to the clinic with a history of recurrent infections and easy fatiguability for 6 months. The peripheral film demonstrated peculiar monocytes twice the size of mature lymphocytes with round nuclei, abundant cytoplasm, and circumferential projections. An attempt to perform bone marrow aspiration revealed a dry tap. What is the most likely diagnosis for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Infectious mononucleosis","bool":false},{"option":"Prolymphocytic leukemia","bool":false}],"id":303},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A patient presents with chipmunk-like facies and a crew-cut appearance of the skull on X-ray. Laboratory investigations show increased fetal hemoglobin (HbF). What is the most likely underlying cause?","answers":[{"option":"Beta-thalassemia minor","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-thalassemia major","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false}],"id":304},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A child suffering from beta-thalassemia is most likely to present the clinical features at the age of:","answers":[{"option":"10 to 12 months after birth","bool":false},{"option":"few months before the birth","bool":false},{"option":"6 to 9 months after birth","bool":true},{"option":"In middle age","bool":false},{"option":"1 year after birth","bool":false}],"id":305},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following gene products is seen in chronic myelogenous leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"BCL-2","bool":false},{"option":"Heavy chain Ig and BCL-2","bool":false},{"option":"BCR-ABL","bool":true},{"option":"Heavy chain Ig and c-myc","bool":false},{"option":"c-myc","bool":false}],"id":306},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following diseases is associated with platelet aggregation defect?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic-uremic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Bernard-Soulier syndrome","bool":false}],"id":307},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following blood tests is done to detect sickle cell disease?","answers":[{"option":"flow cytometry","bool":false},{"option":"Serum protein electrophoresis","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":true},{"option":"Schilling test","bool":false},{"option":"Osmotic fragility test","bool":false}],"id":308},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A person exposed to asbestos is more likely to develop which type of cancer?","answers":[{"option":"Oropharyngeal carcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Breast cancer","bool":false},{"option":"Malignant mesothelioma","bool":false},{"option":"Pleural solitary fibrous tumor","bool":false},{"option":"Lung cancer","bool":true}],"id":309},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following drugs does NOT work by inhibiting ADP binding to platelet receptors?","answers":[{"option":"Abciximab","bool":true},{"option":"Prasugrel","bool":false},{"option":"Ticagrelor","bool":false},{"option":"Ticlopidine","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false}],"id":310},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following drugs inhibits only factor Xa?","answers":[{"option":"Rivaroxiban","bool":true},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Unfractionated Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Bivalirudin","bool":false},{"option":"Argatroban","bool":false}],"id":311},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following drugs is a platelet aggregating inhibitor?","answers":[{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Argatroban","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":true},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Dabigatran","bool":false}],"id":312},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements best describe compliance with a drug?","answers":[{"option":"Doctors and patients needs are fully articulated","bool":true},{"option":"By telling its side effects","bool":false},{"option":"By telling its outcomes","bool":false},{"option":"Give details about the alternative treatments","bool":false},{"option":"By telling the diagnosis to the patient","bool":false}],"id":313},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following set of people are most vulnerable to indoor air pollution?","answers":[{"option":"Middle aged men","bool":false},{"option":"Elderly","bool":false},{"option":"Any aged person","bool":false},{"option":"Women and children","bool":true},{"option":"Pregnant women","bool":false}],"id":314},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Stage IV of Hodgkin lymphoma has a prognosis of:","answers":[{"option":"60 to 70 %","bool":true},{"option":"10 to 15 %","bool":false},{"option":"70 to 90 %","bool":false},{"option":"20 to 40 %","bool":false},{"option":"0 to 10 %","bool":false}],"id":315},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is diapedesis?","answers":[{"option":"Attachment of leukocytes to endothelial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Movement of leukocytes into the tissues","bool":false},{"option":"Recruitment of leukocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Migration of leukocytes through the endothelium","bool":true},{"option":"Leukocytes aggregation","bool":false}],"id":316},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following tumors is the neoplasm of T helper cells?","answers":[{"option":"Mantle cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Marginal zone lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Burkitt lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Follicular lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Sézary syndrome","bool":true}],"id":317},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"In which of the following condition mean corpuscular volume (MCV) is low?","answers":[{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Folate deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false}],"id":318},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Vitamin K deficiency leads to:","answers":[{"option":"Increased bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"Increased PT and PTT","bool":true},{"option":"Decreased platelet count","bool":false},{"option":"Increased PT","bool":false},{"option":"Increased PTT","bool":false}],"id":319},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the best test for disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)?","answers":[{"option":"Increased fibrinogen concentration","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased PT and PTT","bool":false},{"option":"D-dimer","bool":true},{"option":"International normalized ratio (INR)","bool":false},{"option":"Increased coagulation factors","bool":false}],"id":320},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Low erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) represents:","answers":[{"option":"Increased hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Increased red blood cell count","bool":false},{"option":"Increased hematocrit","bool":false},{"option":"No rouleaux formation","bool":true},{"option":"Rouleaux formation","bool":false}],"id":321},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Heinz bodies in erythrocytes are characteristic features of:","answers":[{"option":"Glutathione reductase deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Glutathione peroxidase deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"G6PD deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Glucokinase deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Pyruvate kinase deficiency","bool":false}],"id":322},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following conditions causes the anemia that occurs due to a defect in RBCs' membrane protein?","answers":[{"option":"Warm immunohemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell disease","bool":false},{"option":"Paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria","bool":false},{"option":"Paroxysmal cold hemoglobinuria","bool":false}],"id":323},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following antibodies would be present in a person having blood group B?","answers":[{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Anti Rh antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"IgM and IgG antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Anti B antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Anti A antibodies","bool":true}],"id":324},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the side effect of warfarin?","answers":[{"option":"Ototoxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Neurotoxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Cardiac toxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Myelosuppression","bool":false},{"option":"Severe birth defects","bool":true}],"id":325},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following is not a baseline investigation?","answers":[{"option":"Lipid profile","bool":false},{"option":"Urine DR","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"Lumbar puncture","bool":true},{"option":"HbA1c","bool":false}],"id":326},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 5-year-old presents in an outpatient department with a history of fatigue, headache, and dyspnea. On examination, he was found to be having pale conjunctiva. Upon inquiring her mother she reported that she lost her previous child due to hydrops fetalis. Which thalassemia is incompatible with hydrops fetalis?","answers":[{"option":"Mild Alpha thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Severe Alpha thalassemia","bool":true},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Minor Beta thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Major Beta thalassemia","bool":false}],"id":327},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Macrocytic cells are the most common findings in megaloblastic anemia. Which of the following statements best describe about its cause?","answers":[{"option":"Folate deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B6 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 and folate deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Iron deficiency","bool":false}],"id":328},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements describe leukoerythroblastosis?","answers":[{"option":"Immature red blood cells and white blood cells","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Mature red blood cells and white blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Increased reticulocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":false}],"id":329},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following condition has microcytic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":true},{"option":"Pernicious anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false}],"id":330},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"If a blood smear is taken from a patient having leukoerythroblstosis. What will be the laboratory findings?","answers":[{"option":"Mature white blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Anucleate red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Immature red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Immature red blood cells and white blood cells","bool":true}],"id":331},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Howell-jolly bodies are seen in:","answers":[{"option":"G6PD deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Post splenectomy","bool":true},{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":332},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A baby undergoes circumcision and after the procedure the bleeding is prolonged. Upon inquiry, his brothers and sisters have had the same problem. What test should be done for the assessment?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombin time","bool":false},{"option":"Acute partial thromboplastin time","bool":true},{"option":"Prothrombin time","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet count","bool":false},{"option":"Bleeding time","bool":false}],"id":333},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What will be the risk of inheritance of X-linked disease in the male child if the mother is a carrier and the father is genotypically normal?","answers":[{"option":"25%","bool":false},{"option":"75%","bool":false},{"option":"0%","bool":false},{"option":"50%","bool":true},{"option":"100%","bool":false}],"id":334},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"The extrinsic pathway of coagulation is initiated by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Complement system","bool":false},{"option":"Antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Tissue thromboplastin factor","bool":true},{"option":"Vasoconstriction of venules","bool":false},{"option":"Subendothelial collagen","bool":false}],"id":335},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common cause of disseminated intravascular coagulation?","answers":[{"option":"Bacterial sepsis","bool":true},{"option":"Malignancy","bool":false},{"option":"Hypovolemic shock","bool":false},{"option":"Massive trauma","bool":false},{"option":"Acute pancreatitis","bool":false}],"id":336},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following drug causes cardiac toxicity?","answers":[{"option":"Dactinomycin","bool":false},{"option":"Bleomycin","bool":false},{"option":"Doxorubicin","bool":true},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false}],"id":337},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Hemoglobinuria is a feature of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Intravascular hemolysis","bool":true},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Extravascular hemolysis","bool":false}],"id":338},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Monocytosis is seen in which of the following situations?","answers":[{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberculosis","bool":true},{"option":"Polycythemia vera","bool":false},{"option":"Wilsons disease","bool":false}],"id":339},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the feature of chronic hemolytic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Loss of ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Increased transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemosiderinuria","bool":true},{"option":"Loss of iron","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobinemia","bool":false}],"id":340},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is given to a patient suffering from hemophilia A?","answers":[{"option":"Recombinant factor 8","bool":true},{"option":"Corticosteroid's","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Penicillin","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmapheresis","bool":false}],"id":341},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following substances are required for effective iron absorption?","answers":[{"option":"Folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Ascorbic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Zinc","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium","bool":false},{"option":"Magnesium","bool":false}],"id":342},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statement is not true about acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)?","answers":[{"option":"B-ALL is more common than T-ALL","bool":false},{"option":"Can be B-ALL or T-ALL","bool":false},{"option":"Most common cancer of children","bool":false},{"option":"No blast cell seen in both marrow and periphery","bool":true},{"option":"Has >20% blast cells","bool":false}],"id":343},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following is the feature of aplastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Reticulocytopenia","bool":true},{"option":"Hypercellular bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Increased myeloid cells","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia","bool":false}],"id":344},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following drugs is not used in the treatment of iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Ferrous gluconate","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Ferrous fumarate","bool":false},{"option":"Carbonyl iron","bool":false},{"option":"Ferrous sulfate","bool":false}],"id":345},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"When is brain death declared?","answers":[{"option":"When there is no pulse","bool":false},{"option":"When person stops breathing","bool":false},{"option":"When there is no proper circulation","bool":false},{"option":"When there is loss of brainstem reflexes","bool":true},{"option":"When there is no oxygen delivery","bool":false}],"id":346},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most feared complication in sickle cell disease?","answers":[{"option":"Auto-splenectomy","bool":false},{"option":"Osteomyelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Sequestration crisis","bool":false},{"option":"Dactylitis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute chest syndrome","bool":true}],"id":347},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following term is used for skin bleeding, which is greater than 3 mm but less than 1 cm?","answers":[{"option":"Purpura","bool":true},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Epistaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Ecchymoses","bool":false},{"option":"Petechiae","bool":false}],"id":348},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following are indications of death?","answers":[{"option":"Normal electrocardiogram (ECG)","bool":false},{"option":"Normal electroencephalogram (EEG)","bool":false},{"option":"Stop breathing after an hour","bool":false},{"option":"Flat electroencephalogram (EEG), flat electrocardiogram (ECG), stop breathing within 5 minutes","bool":true},{"option":"Weak pulse","bool":false}],"id":349},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common cause of death in sickle cell disease?","answers":[{"option":"Auto-splenectomy","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic crisis","bool":false},{"option":"Dactylitis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute Chest Syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Sequestration crisis","bool":false}],"id":350},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A middle-aged man presents with excessive bleeding after a minor cut in the OPD. On examination, his lab results showed increased bleeding time but normal prothrombin time (PT) and partial thromboplastin time (PTT). His lab work also showed increased megakaryocytes with no other abnormality in other myeloid lineages. Which of the following condition is most likely present in the patient?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":true},{"option":"Leukopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia","bool":false}],"id":351},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statement represents asphyxial death?","answers":[{"option":"Petechiae and congestion","bool":false},{"option":"Bluish face, congested conjunctiva, and petechial hemorrhage","bool":true},{"option":"Cyanosis only","bool":false},{"option":"Petechiae only","bool":false},{"option":"No petechiae","bool":false}],"id":352},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statement represents mean corpuscular hemoglobin (MCH)?","answers":[{"option":"Average mass of WBCs","bool":false},{"option":"Average mass of hemoglobin in one RBC","bool":true},{"option":"Average volume of one RBC","bool":false},{"option":"Average mass of hemoglobin in RBCs","bool":false},{"option":"Average volume of RBCs","bool":false}],"id":353},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"In which situation the claim of abortion can be false?","answers":[{"option":"Menopausal stage","bool":true},{"option":"Multiparous woman","bool":false},{"option":"Girl in her puberty stage","bool":false},{"option":"Women in her mid 30s","bool":false},{"option":"Woman who just crossed her 20s","bool":false}],"id":354},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is not a platelet inhibitor?","answers":[{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Abciximab","bool":false},{"option":"Acetaminophen","bool":true},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false},{"option":"Ticlopidine","bool":false}],"id":355},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Anti-malarial drugs cause hemolysis in which of the following disease?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphocytic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency","bool":true}],"id":356},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 50-year-old man came to an outpatient department with the complaint of having a rash immediately after taking a shower. Which of the following describes his symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Multiple myeloma","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia Vera","bool":true},{"option":"Gaisbocks syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false}],"id":357},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Henoch-Schonlein purpura is caused by systemic deposition of:","answers":[{"option":"Histamine","bool":false},{"option":"Immune complexes","bool":true},{"option":"Epitheloid cells","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false}],"id":358},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following does not happen in platelet disorders?","answers":[{"option":"Ecchymoses","bool":false},{"option":"Petechiae","bool":false},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Mucosal bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false}],"id":359},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Myelodysplastic syndrome is NOT characterized by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Ineffective lymphopoiesis","bool":true},{"option":"Heterogenous clonal stem cell disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Occurs in elderly","bool":false},{"option":"Ineffective hematopoiesis","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia, neutropenia and thrombocytopenia","bool":false}],"id":360},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"In which of the following condition, alteplase is given?","answers":[{"option":"Prevention of stroke","bool":false},{"option":"Normal bleeding and coagulation time","bool":false},{"option":"Coronary stenting","bool":false},{"option":"Acute ischemic stroke","bool":true},{"option":"Vasodilation","bool":false}],"id":361},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following factors does NOT  promote the sickling of red blood cells?","answers":[{"option":"Obesity","bool":true},{"option":"Viral infection","bool":false},{"option":"Acidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoxia","bool":false},{"option":"Dehydration","bool":false}],"id":362},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"How is alteplase formed?","answers":[{"option":"Made by bacteria in the colon","bool":false},{"option":"Derived from animal sources","bool":false},{"option":"It is naturally found","bool":false},{"option":"Recombinant DNA technology","bool":true},{"option":"Dervied from plant sources","bool":false}],"id":363},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Increased homocysteine levels result in?","answers":[{"option":"Nephrotoxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Ototoxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Osteonecrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Atherosclerosis","bool":true},{"option":"Cataract","bool":false}],"id":364},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 14-year-old boy comes to the outpatient department (OPD) with a complaint of weakness and fever for the past few weeks. On examination, there was increased leukocyte count with normal red blood cell and platelet count. His chest CT further showed a mediastinal mass. Which of the following is the most likely condition from which the boy is suffering from?","answers":[{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic myelogenous leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myelogenous leukemia","bool":false}],"id":365},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements is true about heparin?","answers":[{"option":"Doesn't binds to antithrombin III","bool":false},{"option":"Antidote is vitamin K","bool":false},{"option":"Is antiplatelet drug","bool":false},{"option":"Teratogenic","bool":false},{"option":"Can be given in pregnancy","bool":true}],"id":366},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common clinical manifestation in Von Willebrand's disease?","answers":[{"option":"Gum bleeding","bool":true},{"option":"Joint bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Deep tissue bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Rectal bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Post surgical bleeding","bool":false}],"id":367},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"The triad of symptoms, thrombocytopenia, acute kidney injury and microangiopathic hemolytic anemia, is seen in which of the following condition?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic-uremic syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":false},{"option":"Bernard-Soulier syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":false}],"id":368},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is correct regarding cyclophosphamide?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibitor of hypoxanthine-guanine phosphoribosyltransferase","bool":false},{"option":"Alkylating agent","bool":true},{"option":"Pyrimidine analog","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibitor of dihydrofolate reductase","bool":false},{"option":"IL-2 inhibitor","bool":false}],"id":369},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements is true about fibrinolytics?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"They cause allergy and antibody production","bool":true},{"option":"Urokinase directly inhibits plasminogen","bool":false},{"option":"Streptokinase directly inhibits plasminogen","bool":false},{"option":"Contraindicated in acute myocardial infarction","bool":false}],"id":370},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following condition presents with the usage of platelets and the coagulation factors, along with microangiopathic hemolytic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Bernard-Soulier syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":false},{"option":"hemolytic-uremic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":true}],"id":371},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 20-year-old man whose femur got fractured in a road traffic accident is bleeding profusely from the fracture site. What should he be transfused with?","answers":[{"option":"Packed red cell concentrate","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Whole blood","bool":true},{"option":"Cryoprecipitate","bool":false},{"option":"Pooled platelets","bool":false}],"id":372},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 20-year-old man is brought into the emergency after a road traffic accident. As a result, he is suspected to be infected by tetanus. Which of the following vaccine will be given to this man?","answers":[{"option":"Live attenuated","bool":false},{"option":"Toxoid and immunoglobulin","bool":false},{"option":"Immunoglobulin","bool":false},{"option":"Toxoid","bool":true},{"option":"Dead virus","bool":false}],"id":373},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following best describes the function of interleukins?","answers":[{"option":"To prevent mucosal bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Rolling of white blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Vasodilation of arterioles","bool":false},{"option":"Diapedesis","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotaxis","bool":true}],"id":374},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following would the 2nd line treatment for a patient suffering from sickle cell anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Corticosteroids","bool":false},{"option":"IV vancomycin","bool":false},{"option":"Plasmapheresis","bool":false},{"option":"Hydroxyurea","bool":true},{"option":"Desmopressin","bool":false}],"id":375},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Extramedullary hematopoiesis occurs due to myelodysplastic fibrosis. Which of the following would be the most common site of extramedullary hematopoiesis?","answers":[{"option":"Spleen","bool":true},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false},{"option":"Bones","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Thyroid","bool":false}],"id":376},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Spherocytosis is seen in which other conditions than hereditary spherocytosis?","answers":[{"option":"Infection-induced hemolytic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Autosplenectomy","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":377},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 40-year-old man undergoes successful surgery. On the second postoperative day, he developed a high-grade fever. It was later found out that the doctors had inadvertently left a swab in his abdomen. Which type of negligence is this?","answers":[{"option":"Civil negligence","bool":false},{"option":"Contributory negligence","bool":false},{"option":"Corporate negligence","bool":false},{"option":"Res-Ipsa-Loquotar","bool":false},{"option":"Criminal negligence","bool":true}],"id":378},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 50-year-old man visits a medical center with complaints of dyspnea and fatigue. On examination, he was found to have generalized lymphadenopathy and jaundice. His blood smear showed smudge cells. Which of the following is a complication if a patient suffering is from Chronic lymphocytic leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Pneumonia","bool":false},{"option":"Fever, rash and itchy back","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatosplenomegaly","bool":false}],"id":379},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"The administration of a private hospital does not provide quality instruments to the doctors. Which type of negligence is this?","answers":[{"option":"Criminal negligence","bool":false},{"option":"Corporate negligence","bool":true},{"option":"Res ipsa loquitur","bool":false},{"option":"Contributory negligence","bool":false},{"option":"Civil negligence","bool":false}],"id":380},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is the World Health Organization's criteria for anemia in infants?","answers":[{"option":"Hb < 11.0 gm/dL","bool":true},{"option":"Hb < 14.0 gm/dL","bool":false},{"option":"Hb < 12.0 gm/dL","bool":false},{"option":"Hb < 10.0 gm/dL","bool":false},{"option":"Hb < 13.5 gm/dL","bool":false}],"id":381},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"How much hemoglobin and hematocrit are increased respectively when one pint of blood is transfused?","answers":[{"option":"3 mg/dl and 1 %","bool":false},{"option":"0 mg/dl and 2 %","bool":false},{"option":"2 mg/dl and 0 %","bool":false},{"option":"5 mg/dl and 10 %","bool":false},{"option":"1 mg/dl and 3 %","bool":true}],"id":382},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Ringed sideroblasts are seen in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sideroblastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false}],"id":383},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"The lacunar variant of Reed-Sternberg (RS) cells is found in:","answers":[{"option":"Mixed cellularity","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocyte rich","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocyte depletion","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocyte predominant","bool":false},{"option":"Nodular sclerosis","bool":true}],"id":384},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 14-year-old boy presents to the outpatient department (OPD) with weakness and fever. On examination, his bone marrow showed 80% hypercellularity but 3% myeloblasts. Which of the following condition is most likely associated with his symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Acute myelogenous leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myelogenous leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false}],"id":385},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A man presents to the emergency with weakness. On examination, Reed-Sternberg cells were found along with swelling of a lymph node. There were no systemic symptoms reported. The doctor concluded his condition as Hodgkin lymphoma. What is the stage of lymphoma in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Stage IB","bool":false},{"option":"Stage IV","bool":false},{"option":"Stage II","bool":false},{"option":"Stage IA","bool":true},{"option":"Stage III","bool":false}],"id":386},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"How is acute leukemia differentiated by chronic leukemia?","answers":[{"option":"Presence of blast cells","bool":true},{"option":"Aggressive nature","bool":false},{"option":"Size","bool":false},{"option":"Metastasis","bool":false},{"option":"Location","bool":false}],"id":387},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following Gustafson's method is most reliable?","answers":[{"option":"Cement apposition","bool":false},{"option":"Loosening of teeth","bool":false},{"option":"Root transparency","bool":true},{"option":"Root resorption","bool":false},{"option":"Gradual wearing out of teeth","bool":false}],"id":388},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Auer rods in the cytoplasm are a classical finding of which of the following neoplasms?","answers":[{"option":"Hodgkin Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myelogenous leukemia (CML)","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL)","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia (AML)","bool":true}],"id":389},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of these is not prepared from human blood?","answers":[{"option":"Cryoprecipitate","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Packed cells","bool":false},{"option":"Recombinant factor VIII","bool":true}],"id":390},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A patient having B-Thalassemia on regular transfusions starts to develop urticaria in the past 4 to 5 months. Which of the following should be given to him before his next transfusion session?","answers":[{"option":"Antihistamines","bool":true},{"option":"Anti Rh negative antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Antimalarial","bool":false},{"option":"Washed blood","bool":false},{"option":"Corticosteroids","bool":false}],"id":391},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is the daily requirement of iron in pregnant females?","answers":[{"option":"14.7 mg/dl","bool":false},{"option":"0.4 mg/dl","bool":false},{"option":"2 mg/dl","bool":false},{"option":"7 mg/dl","bool":false},{"option":"3.4 mg/dl","bool":true}],"id":392},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A body is found in the jungle resisting to blanch on pressure. How many hours have elapsed after the death of this person?","answers":[{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"1 to 3 hours","bool":false},{"option":"24 hours","bool":false},{"option":"10 to 12 hours","bool":true},{"option":"5 to 6 hours","bool":false}],"id":393},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Koilonychia is seen in which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Polycythemia","bool":false},{"option":"Neutropenia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocytosis","bool":false}],"id":394},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is used as a corrosive used for cleaning rust?","answers":[{"option":"Aluminum","bool":false},{"option":"Oxalic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Hydrogen peroxide","bool":false},{"option":"Zinc oxide","bool":false},{"option":"Copper","bool":false}],"id":395},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Heparin works in association with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Calmodulin","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Dense proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Antithrombin III","bool":true}],"id":396},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements best describes neoadjuvant chemotherapy?","answers":[{"option":"Chemotherapy given during surgery","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotherapy given as a supplemental treatment after surgery or radiation","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotherapy given in low doses to prolong remission","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotherapy given as a supplemental treatment during radiation","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotherapy given prior to surgery in an attempt to shrink the tumor","bool":true}],"id":397},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is NOT the most common complication of chemotherapy?","answers":[{"option":"Vomiting","bool":false},{"option":"Alopecia","bool":false},{"option":"Bladder cancer","bool":true},{"option":"Stomatitis","bool":false},{"option":"Myelosuppression","bool":false}],"id":398},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is associated with thalassemia disease?","answers":[{"option":"Defective globin chains","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Deficient globin chains","bool":true}],"id":399},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A man presents to the emergency with tenderness on his left upper quadrant and yellow discoloration of the skin.  On examination, he is found to have icterus and splenomegaly. His lab results show increased total bilirubin levels but normal direct bilirubin. His blood smear further show an increased number of reticulocytes. Which of the following is the most likely reason for this?","answers":[{"option":"Thromocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolysis","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":400},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A baby is born to a full-term mother through vaginal delivery. He has tortuous and dilated veins that are widely distributed on his skin and mucous membranes. Which of the following is the most likely condition that the baby is suffering from?","answers":[{"option":"Sickle cell disease","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia","bool":true},{"option":"Varicose veins","bool":false}],"id":401},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"What is the diagnostic test for Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"The site of lymph node involved","bool":false},{"option":"Fine Needle Aspiration Cytology (FNAC)","bool":false},{"option":"Checking tenderness of the lymph nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Excision biopsy with histopathology","bool":true},{"option":"Biopsy only","bool":false}],"id":402},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"Which one of the following is the surest method of identification?","answers":[{"option":"Blood group","bool":false},{"option":"Sex","bool":false},{"option":"Belongings","bool":false},{"option":"Age","bool":false},{"option":"Fingerprinting","bool":true}],"id":403},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"If a lady had a missed abortion, which of the following is the most suitable transfusion for her?","answers":[{"option":"Cryoprecipitate","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets and packed red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Only platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Packed red blood cells","bool":true}],"id":404},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A female patient is brought to the clinic after a snake bite with complaints of oozing blood from the wound site, widespread pinpoint and patchy red spots on her skin, and dyspnea. She appears lethargic, has cold skin, and is diaphoretic. She is immediately diagnosed with disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) secondary to envenomation by the snake. \r\n\r\nWhich of the following is the most appropriate step in the management of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Oral antivenom","bool":false},{"option":"Packed red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous antivenom","bool":true}],"id":405},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 55-year-old patient is recovering from non-valvular atrial fibrillation. She is currently on warfarin and esmolol. Her most reason INR level = 7. \r\nWhat is the next best step in the management of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Add vitamin K antagonist","bool":false},{"option":"Stop warfarin","bool":true},{"option":"Add heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Add digoxin","bool":false},{"option":"Transfuse fresh frozen plasma","bool":false}],"id":406},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 50-year-old female presents to the clinic with complaints of hemoptysis and hematuria.  Upon further inquiry, the patient tells you that she was diagnosed with allergic rhinitis when she was 26 years old. Which of the following is the best diagnostic test?","answers":[{"option":"Serum antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibodies (ANCA)","bool":true},{"option":"Serum antinuclear antibody (ANA)","bool":false},{"option":"ESR and CRP","bool":false},{"option":"Serum anti glomerular basement membrane (anti-GBM) antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"IgM antibodies","bool":false}],"id":407},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 14-year-old boy presents to the clinic due to excessive bleeding from a wound. He tells you that he often gets bruises, especially on his knees and elbows. This patient most likely has a deficiency of factor VIII. What is the inheritance pattern of this disease?","answers":[{"option":"Mitochondrial inheritance","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked dominant inheritance","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":true}],"id":408},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 71-year-old male presents to the clinic with complaints of unintentional weight loss, recurrent infections, lethargy, and night sweats. On examination, he has painless cervical and supraclavicular lymph node enlargements and the liver border can be palpated 1cm below the costal margin. \r\nLaboratory investigations show WBC = 15000 cells/mm3, lymphocytes = 8000 cells/mm3, Hb = 9 g/dL, blood smear shows a high percentage of small, mature lymphocytes, and the presence of smudge cells. \r\n\r\nWhat is the most likely diagnosis of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL)","bool":true},{"option":"Burkitt's lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)","bool":false},{"option":"Diffuse large B cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Hairy cell lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":409},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 29 year-old-patient, who is 15 days post-op after delivering a baby via c-section, presents to the clinic with complaints of localized swelling in her right lower limb. The swelling has increased in size over 2 days and is associated with pain and erythema. On examination, the swelling is warm to the touch and tender, and the circumference of the affected leg is 5 cm larger than the unaffected leg. \r\nWhich of the following is the preferred initial test in this patient for establishing diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"CT angiography of lower limb","bool":false},{"option":"CT venography of lower limb","bool":false},{"option":"Serum D-dimer levels","bool":false},{"option":"CT angiography of chest","bool":false},{"option":"Doppler ultrasound scan of lower limb","bool":true}],"id":410},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A patient presents to the clinic with complaints of fatigue and exertional dyspnea. On examination, she has yellow discoloration of skin and sclera, subconjunctival pallor, and her spleen can be palpated 2cm below the costal margin. \r\nThe physician suspects intravascular hemolytic anemia and prescribes the relevant laboratory workup. \r\nWhich of the following findings does the physician not expect to see on laboratory reports?","answers":[{"option":"Elevated serum haptoglobin","bool":true},{"option":"Elevated corrected reticulocyte count","bool":false},{"option":"Increased urinary urobilinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Elevated serum indirect (unconjugated) bilirubin","bool":false},{"option":"Elevated serum lactate dehydrogenase (LDH)","bool":false}],"id":411},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 40-year-old male presents with presents to the clinic with complaints of fever, vomiting, and fatigue for 5 days. On examination, there are petechiae and pallor. Laboratory reports show Hb = 9 g/dL, Platelets = 19,000/mm3, Cr = 6 mg/dL. \r\n\r\nWhat is the most likely cause of this patient's anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":true},{"option":"Macroangiopathic hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":false}],"id":412},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 45-year-old patient presents with a history of recurrent infections, easy bruising, and persistent fatigue. Further evaluation reveals anemia. What is the most likely cause of these symptoms in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Iron-deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":true}],"id":413},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2019"],"question":"A 12-year-old patient presents with a history of fatigue and yellowish discoloration of the sclera. On abdominal examination, splenomegaly is appreciated. An electrophoresis test is performed to evaluate the hemoglobin levels. What is the expected electrophoresis finding in a patient with beta-thalassemia major?","answers":[{"option":"Elevated hemoglobin C (HbC) levels","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased hemoglobin S (HbS) levels","bool":false},{"option":"Elevated hemoglobin A (HbA) levels","bool":false},{"option":"Elevated hemoglobin A2 (HbA2) levels","bool":false},{"option":"Elevated hemoglobin F (HbF) levels","bool":true}],"id":414},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 9-year-old boy is brought to the outpatient department after he developed prominent bruises on his extremities. There is a history of a recent viral infection. Labs show normal values of both prothrombin time (PT) and activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT). What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Bone marrow aplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-platelet antibodies","bool":true},{"option":"Von-Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false}],"id":415},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 25-year-old female with a history of two miscarriages develops deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in her leg. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Antiphospholipid syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Behcet's syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Rheumatoid arthritis","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":false},{"option":"Overlap syndrome","bool":false}],"id":416},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A person with polycythemia vera will have which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Yellow and jaundiced","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Pink in colour","bool":false},{"option":"Well oxygenated","bool":false},{"option":"Cyanotic due to sluggish blood flow","bool":true}],"id":417},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"How many subtypes is Hodgkin lymphoma is divided into?","answers":[{"option":"Four subtypes","bool":false},{"option":"Two subtypes","bool":false},{"option":"Three subtypes","bool":false},{"option":"Five subtypes","bool":true},{"option":"Ten subtypes","bool":false}],"id":418},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Conversion of plasminogen to plasmin is inhibited by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Alteplase","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Aminocaproic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":false}],"id":419},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following antibodies is cold-type hemolytic anemia due to?","answers":[{"option":"IgM antibodies","bool":true},{"option":"IgG antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"IgD antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"IgA antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"IgE antibodies","bool":false}],"id":420},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"The levels of protein C and protein S depend on which vitamin?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin E","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin A","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin D","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false}],"id":421},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"What number of teeth are in a eight-year-old child's mouth?","answers":[{"option":"24","bool":true},{"option":"20","bool":false},{"option":"16","bool":false},{"option":"30","bool":false},{"option":"12","bool":false}],"id":422},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Essentially all endemic forms of Burkitt lymphoma are associated with which pathogen?","answers":[{"option":"HCV","bool":false},{"option":"EBV","bool":true},{"option":"HTCL-I","bool":false},{"option":"HIV","bool":false},{"option":"HBV","bool":false}],"id":423},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Polycythemia vera is strongly associated with an activating point mutation in which of the following genes?","answers":[{"option":"Tyrosine kinase ABL","bool":false},{"option":"p53","bool":false},{"option":"Tyrosine kinase JAK2","bool":true},{"option":"Tyrosine kinase JAKI","bool":false},{"option":"Tyrosine kinase","bool":false}],"id":424},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A young female presents with a palpable cervical lymph node, and in her biopsy reveals Reed- Sternberg's cells. These cells are derived from which of the following cell types?","answers":[{"option":"Plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"T-lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"ß-lymphocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Eosinophil","bool":false}],"id":425},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Basophil leukocytosis is an indication for:","answers":[{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Myeloproliferative disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic infection","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myelogenous leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Stenle inflammation","bool":false}],"id":426},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is responsible to facilitate absorption of oral iron preparations?","answers":[{"option":"Phosphoric acid","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of food in stomach","bool":false},{"option":"Antacids","bool":false},{"option":"Tetracyclines","bool":false},{"option":"Ascorbic acid","bool":true}],"id":427},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A child is diagnosed with non-Hodgkin lymphoma. He has generalized lymphadenopathy. Chest X-ray shows a mediastinal mass and CT abdomen shows enlarged, multiple mesentric, and para aortic lymph nodes. What is the most likely stage of the disease?","answers":[{"option":"Stage III","bool":true},{"option":"Stage I","bool":false},{"option":"Stage IV","bool":false},{"option":"Stage V","bool":false},{"option":"Stage II","bool":false}],"id":428},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Extravascular hemolysis occurs mainly in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"GIT","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph node","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":true},{"option":"Blood vessels","bool":false}],"id":429},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Hemoglobin (HbH) disease is caused by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Deletion of three alpha-globin genes","bool":true},{"option":"Deletion of beta-globin genes","bool":false},{"option":"Deletion of gamma-globin genes","bool":false},{"option":"Point mutation in a single alpha-globin gene","bool":false},{"option":"Deletion of delta-globin genes","bool":false}],"id":430},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Systemic viral infection, particularly in children often produce which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Acute lymphadenitis in inguinal region","bool":false},{"option":"Acute mesenteric adenitis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphadenitis in axillary region","bool":false},{"option":"Acute generalized lymphadenopathy","bool":true},{"option":"Acute lymphadenitis in cervical region","bool":false}],"id":431},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 45-year-old man with acute myocardial infarction is given alteplase. Which statement best describes its effect?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibition of platelet thromboxane production","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibits synthesis of vitamin K-dependent coagulation factors","bool":false},{"option":"Prevents aggregation of adjacent platelets by blocking glycoprotein IIb/IIIa receptor","bool":false},{"option":"Blockade of ADP-platelet receptor","bool":false},{"option":"Rapidly activates plasmin","bool":true}],"id":432},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 2-year-old child comes to the hospital for circumcision. His two brothers also had bleeding diathesis. Which test should be done?","answers":[{"option":"D-dimers","bool":false},{"option":"Clotting time","bool":false},{"option":"aPTT","bool":true},{"option":"Bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"Urea clot lysis test","bool":false}],"id":433},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"ABO incompatibility occurs in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Post transfusion plupine","bool":false},{"option":"Transfusion of bacterial contaminated blood product","bool":false},{"option":"Febrile non-hemolytic transfusion reactions","bool":false},{"option":"Anaphylactic reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Acute hemolytic transfusion reactions","bool":true}],"id":434},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 30-year-old female admitted with anemic failure for which she received six units of stored whole blood. After 24 hours she develops twitching on the face and carpopedal spasm of hands. What is the best treatment option?","answers":[{"option":"Give her I/V slowly calcium gluconate infusion","bool":true},{"option":"Give her I/V diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Give her I/V magnesium sulphate","bool":false},{"option":"Give her I/V 5% dextrose water","bool":false},{"option":"Give her I/V normal saline","bool":false}],"id":435},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 25-year-old female presents with sudden onset pain in the right upper limb on examination right upper limb is pale, cold, extremely tender with absent radial and brachial pulses on the right side. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Myositis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute limb ischemia","bool":true},{"option":"Venous thrombosis","bool":false},{"option":"Osteomyelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Humerus fracture","bool":false}],"id":436},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"What is the most appropriate treatment for a 5-year-old child with hereditary spherocytosis, large spleen, with hemoglobin mostly remaining at 7-9gm/dl, and reticulocyte count at 12-15%?","answers":[{"option":"Hydroxyurea","bool":false},{"option":"Regular blood transfusions with deferral","bool":true},{"option":"Regular blood transfusions","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow transplant","bool":false},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":false}],"id":437},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"For a functional platelet disorder, which of the following is a correct statement?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombocytopenia, PT and APTT will be normal","bool":false},{"option":"Normal platelet count, PT & APTT will be prolonged","bool":false},{"option":"Normal platelet count, APTT will be prolonged","bool":false},{"option":"Normal or low platelet count, PT & APTT will be normal","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia, only PT will be prolonged","bool":false}],"id":438},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which investigation(s) is/are the first step investigating a case of thrombosis?","answers":[{"option":"Antiphospholipid antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Lupus anticoagulant","bool":false},{"option":"D-dimers","bool":true},{"option":"Prothrombin time","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V Leiden","bool":false}],"id":439},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following foods has the best iron absorption from the intestines?","answers":[{"option":"Pomegranate","bool":false},{"option":"Pulses","bool":false},{"option":"Red meat","bool":true},{"option":"Oranges","bool":false},{"option":"Mangoes","bool":false}],"id":440},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is correct regarding nutritional anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Most common cause is folate deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"It is a disease syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Does not present with signs and symptms","bool":false},{"option":"Most common cause is iron deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Cannot be recovered","bool":false}],"id":441},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"What is the most common chromosomal change in acute lymphoblastic leukemia (ALL)?","answers":[{"option":"t(14; 18)","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperploidy","bool":true},{"option":"t(11; 18)","bool":false},{"option":"Trisomy 12","bool":false},{"option":"t(8; 14)","bool":false}],"id":442},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following inherited bleeding disorders almost always occurs in males?","answers":[{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VII deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":true},{"option":"Factor XIII deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V deficiency","bool":false}],"id":443},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following triggers the extrinsic clotting mechanism?","answers":[{"option":"Platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Thromboplastin","bool":true},{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"White blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Adenosine","bool":false}],"id":444},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Corticosteroid-induced immunosuppression involves which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Modification of T cell mediated response","bool":false},{"option":"B-lymphocyte activation inhibition","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased production of interleukins","bool":false},{"option":"All of these","bool":true},{"option":"Mast cell stabilization","bool":false}],"id":445},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 64-year-old male presents to the hospital with excruciating back pain, His erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR) and creatinine levels are markedly raised. The clinical diagnosis made by the physician is multiple myeloma. What will be the most characteristic findings on his serum protein electrophoresis?","answers":[{"option":"Polyclonal broad band in gamma region","bool":false},{"option":"Single sharp discrete band in gamma region","bool":true},{"option":"Single sharp band in alpha region","bool":false},{"option":"Single sharp band in beta 2 region","bool":false},{"option":"Single sharp band in albumin region","bool":false}],"id":446},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"The subdivision of lymphomas into Hodgkin's and Non-Hodgkin's lymphomas is based on the\r\nhistological presence of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"B-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Reed–Sternberg cells","bool":true},{"option":"Kupffer cells","bool":false},{"option":"Natural killer cells (NK-cells)","bool":false},{"option":"T-cells","bool":false}],"id":447},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"In myeloproliferative disorders, there is a proliferation of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Myeloid progenitors","bool":true},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false}],"id":448},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"An 8-year-old child is brought to the hospital with complaints of fever for 2 months along with hepatomegaly and splenomegaly. Investigations show the following: Hb=4.8 gm/dl, TLC=1700/HPF, platelets=38000. Peripheral smear shows microcytic anemia with blast cells. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sepsis/disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)","bool":false},{"option":"Typhoid fever","bool":false},{"option":"Malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Acute leukemia","bool":true}],"id":449},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Tests for coagulation profile usually include; bleeding time, clotting time, prothrombin time (PT) and\r\nactivated partial prothrombin time (aPTT). Prolonged bleeding time with normal PT and APTT is indicative\r\nof which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Von-Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":true},{"option":"Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Vascular disorders","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false}],"id":450},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"The process of margination of neutrophils is mediated by the reaction between which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Integrin and interleukin-7 (IL-7)","bool":false},{"option":"Gamma interferon and integrin","bool":false},{"option":"Intracellular adhesion molecule-I and chemokines","bool":false},{"option":"Selectins and integrins","bool":true},{"option":"Integrin and major basic protein","bool":false}],"id":451},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 72-year-old man is brought to the emergency department with sudden onset of acute arterial occlusions of the right lower limb leading to gangrene of the lower leg and foot. He has lens subluxation and a long tapering finger. What is the most probable cause of this acute arterial occlusion?","answers":[{"option":"Homocysteinemia","bool":true},{"option":"Protein C deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Factor V leiden mutant gene","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia vera","bool":false},{"option":"Antiphospholipid antibody syndrome","bool":false}],"id":452},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"What is the replacement source in the therapy of hemophilia A?","answers":[{"option":"Recombinant factor VIII products","bool":true},{"option":"Recombinant factor VII A","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Prothrombrin complex concentrates","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin K","bool":false}],"id":453},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following best suits the definition of hemolysis?","answers":[{"option":"Premature destruction of red blood cells (RBCs)","bool":true},{"option":"Loss of blood via bleeding","bool":false},{"option":"Peripheral destruction of platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Extravasation of blood in skin","bool":false},{"option":"Under production of red blood cells","bool":false}],"id":454},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"What is the prime objective in bone marrow transplantation?","answers":[{"option":"Get rid of the primary disease","bool":true},{"option":"Make patient pancytopenic","bool":false},{"option":"To inhibit graft versus host disease (GVHD)","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotherapy to kill the malignant disease","bool":false},{"option":"To initiate graft versus host disease (GVHD)","bool":false}],"id":455},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"The indication for hematopoietic stem cell transplants does not include the following?","answers":[{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Hematologic malignancies","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Non-hematologic cancers","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false}],"id":456},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 70-year-old male presents to the hospital with severe backache. His investigations reveal Hb=7 gm/dl, creatinine=2 mg/dL, ESR= 110 mm/hour. What other finding is most likely to be found on investigations?","answers":[{"option":"Hypernatremia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypocalcemia","bool":false},{"option":"Raised serum alkaline phosphatase","bool":false},{"option":"Hypercalcemia","bool":true},{"option":"Bone scan showing increased uptake","bool":false}],"id":457},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"According to the expanded program of immunization (EPI), the second dose of the measles vaccine is recommended to be given at what age?","answers":[{"option":"1 year","bool":false},{"option":"15 months","bool":true},{"option":"6 months","bool":false},{"option":"18 month","bool":false},{"option":"9 months","bool":false}],"id":458},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"What is the best long term treatment in a patient with cerebrovascular accident (CVA) after arterial thrombosis with anti-phospholipid syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Physiotherapy","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":true},{"option":"Lipid-lowering medicine","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false}],"id":459},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is least likely to be a clinical feature of aplastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Blood blisters in the mouth","bool":false},{"option":"Bleeding gums and epistaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Ecchymoses","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphadenopathy and hepatosplenomegaly","bool":true},{"option":"Bleeding with minimal trauma","bool":false}],"id":460},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"In hemophilia, there is a prolongation of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"PT, aPTT, and bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"Bleeding time","bool":false},{"option":"aPTT","bool":true},{"option":"PT and aPTT","bool":false},{"option":"PT","bool":false}],"id":461},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"An 11-year-old child is diagnosed with acute lymphoblastic leukemia. Which of the following is the most important factor in classifying leukemia as a high-risk group?","answers":[{"option":"Platelet count less than 50,000","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocyte count less than 1500","bool":false},{"option":"Age of the child between 1-10 years","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocyte count greater than 50,000","bool":true},{"option":"Hemoglobin less than 5 gm/dl","bool":false}],"id":462},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is correct regarding the mixed cellularity variant of Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Immunophenotype is not classical","bool":false},{"option":"The mononuclear variant of Reed-Sternberg cells is seen","bool":true},{"option":"Not associated with Epstein–Barr virus (EBV)","bool":false},{"option":"It is seen in 5% of cases","bool":false},{"option":"Monotonous cellular infiltrate is the hallmark","bool":false}],"id":463},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) is found in 30-40% of cases of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hairy cell leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Burkitt's lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Kaposi's sarcoma","bool":false}],"id":464},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Immune cell antigen CD4 is associated with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Natural killer cells","bool":false},{"option":"Mature T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"Thymocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Helper T-cells","bool":true},{"option":"Cytotoxic T-cells","bool":false}],"id":465},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is not a presentation of a patient with a disorder of primary hemostasis?","answers":[{"option":"Petechia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemarthrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Menorrhagia","bool":false},{"option":"Ecchymosis","bool":false},{"option":"Gum bleeding","bool":false}],"id":466},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A patient has presented with iron deficiency anemia and was prescribed treatment with iron supplements. Which single test would show early response to the treatment?","answers":[{"option":"Total Iron Binding capacity","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocyte count","bool":true},{"option":"Blood Complete picture","bool":false},{"option":"Iron","bool":false}],"id":467},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following statements is correct regarding vitamin B12 and folic acid?","answers":[{"option":"Deficiency of either vitamin B12 or folic acid impairs DNA synthesis","bool":true},{"option":"Pernicious anemia should be treated with folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Deficiency of folic acid is usually associated with neurological abnormalities","bool":false},{"option":"Lack of plasma transferrin causes the malabsorption of vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"To treat patient with a deficiency of intrinsic factor, vitamin B12 should be administered orally","bool":false}],"id":468},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"In chronic myeloid leukemia, there is a predominant proliferation of which cells?","answers":[{"option":"Eosinophil precursors","bool":false},{"option":"Erythroid precursors","bool":false},{"option":"Basophil precursors","bool":true},{"option":"Granulocyte precursors","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophil and myeloid precursors","bool":false}],"id":469},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Virchowis Node is pathological enlargement of:","answers":[{"option":"Right jugulodigastric lymph node","bool":false},{"option":"Left jugulodigastric lymph node","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior Cervical Chain Lymph Node","bool":false},{"option":"Right Supra-Clavicular Lymph Node","bool":false},{"option":"Left Supra-Clavicular Lymph Node","bool":true}],"id":470},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Why does sickling occur in sickle cell anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Polycythaemia","bool":false},{"option":"Increase red cell counts","bool":false},{"option":"Low oxygen tension in tissues","bool":true},{"option":"Increased haemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"RBC shape","bool":false}],"id":471},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"In graft versus host (GVHD) disease, which organ is most commonly affected?","answers":[{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Skin","bool":false},{"option":"GIT","bool":true},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Heart","bool":false}],"id":472},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 50-year-old male was diagnosed with a case of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. His hemoglobin was 6 gm/dL. Peripheral smear shows anemia. Which type of anemia are non-Hodgkin lymphomas mostly associated with?","answers":[{"option":"Anemia due to bone marrow infiltration","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":true},{"option":"Dry induced anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":false}],"id":473},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Best indicator of air pollution is/are:","answers":[{"option":"Smoke, suspended particles and SO2","bool":false},{"option":"Carbon monoxide","bool":false},{"option":"Sulphur dioxide","bool":false},{"option":"Particulate matter","bool":true},{"option":"Methane","bool":false}],"id":474},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 21-year-old female has a history of recurrent blood transfusion. On examination she is anemic and her spleen is enlarged 6 cm below the left costal margin. Hb=7.3 g/dL, MCV=50 fL, reticulocyte count=3.5%. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Pyruvate kinase deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":true}],"id":475},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following foods have best iron absorption from the intestine?","answers":[{"option":"Mangoes","bool":false},{"option":"Pulses","bool":false},{"option":"Pomogrenate","bool":false},{"option":"Oranges","bool":false},{"option":"Red meat","bool":true}],"id":476},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 1-year-old child is recently diagnosed with beta-thalassemia major. Which of the following will be the most characteristic findings on a peripheral film of the child?","answers":[{"option":"Poikilocytosis, hypochromia, microcytosis, target cells, and fragmented red blood cells","bool":true},{"option":"Hyporchromia, microcytosis, and sickled cells","bool":false},{"option":"Bite cells, blister cells, and spherocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Microspherocytes, polychromasia, and nucleated red blood vells","bool":false},{"option":"Macro-ovalocytes with nuclear hypersegmentation","bool":false}],"id":477},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"What is the primary mechanism by which heparin prevents coagulation of blood?","answers":[{"option":"Direct inhibition of the conversion of prothrombin to thrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of calcium","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of factors XIIa and XIIIa","bool":false},{"option":"Facilitation of antithrombin III mediated inhibition of factor Xa and thrombin","bool":true},{"option":"Activation of antithrombin III to inhibit factors IX and XI","bool":false}],"id":478},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 5-year-old child with a known case of eczema also develops rhinitis and gets asthmatic with seasonal change. She is brought to the outpatient department and a complete blood count is advised. Which cell would be in high number is this case?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinphils","bool":true},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false}],"id":479},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A dead body is brought to the mortuary for post mortem examination, having post mortem rigidity present in the whole body from head to toe. What is the estimated time since the death?","answers":[{"option":"24-36 hours","bool":false},{"option":"36-48 hours","bool":false},{"option":"4-18 hours","bool":false},{"option":"12-24 hours","bool":true},{"option":"2-4 hours","bool":false}],"id":480},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"What are the differentiating features of the female pelvis?","answers":[{"option":"Obturator foramen is large","bool":false},{"option":"Sub-pubic angle V-shaped","bool":false},{"option":"Ischial tuberosity is inverted","bool":false},{"option":"Pre-auricular sulcus less prominent","bool":false},{"option":"Sub-pubic angle U-shaped, and obtuse","bool":true}],"id":481},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 40-year-old male bed-bound from paraplegia is diagnosed with deep vein thrombosis (DVT) in his right leg. He develops a sudden onset of shortness of breath. A subsequent diagnosis of pulmonary embolism is made. What will be the most common initial electrocardiography (ECG) finding?","answers":[{"option":"S1Q3T3 pattern","bool":false},{"option":"ST segment elevation","bool":false},{"option":"Right bundle branch block","bool":false},{"option":"Sinus tachycardia","bool":true},{"option":"Non-specific T wave inversion","bool":false}],"id":482},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 20-year-old male presents to the outpatient department with a history of fever and night sweats for the past two months. On examination, multiple cervical lymph nodes are palpable which are painless and matted. Which of the following is the single best diagnostic option?","answers":[{"option":"Mantoux test","bool":false},{"option":"High levels of erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR)","bool":false},{"option":"Fine needle aspiration cytology (FNAC)","bool":false},{"option":"Excisional biopsy of the node","bool":true},{"option":"Supportive evidence by chest X-ray (CXR)","bool":false}],"id":483},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is the correct sequence of steps in bone marrow transplantation?","answers":[{"option":"Collection, chemotherapy, infusion","bool":false},{"option":"Collection, processing, cryopreservation, infusion","bool":false},{"option":"Collection, cryopreservation, chemotherapy, infusion","bool":false},{"option":"Collection, processing, cryopreservation, chemotherapy, infusion","bool":true},{"option":"Collection, infusion","bool":false}],"id":484},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Primary immune thrombocytopenia occurs due to which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Systemic lupus erythmatosus (SLE)","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Auto-antibodies","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false}],"id":485},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 35-year-old male known case of chronic myeloid leukemia shows massive splenomegaly on clinical examination. Complete blood count (CBC) reveals WBC count=165x10^9/L, Hb= 9.0 gm/dL and platelets=510 X10^3. Which of the following targeted therapy is specific for chronic myeloid leukemia patients?","answers":[{"option":"Jak-2 inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-CD20 antibody","bool":false},{"option":"Check point inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Tyrosine kinase inhibitors","bool":true},{"option":"Thrombopoietin receptor agonists","bool":false}],"id":486},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 60-year-old patient presented with anorexia, weakness, paraesthesia, and mental changes. His tongue was red, tendon reflexes were diminished, and hemoglobin was 6 gm/dL with large red cells and hypersegmented neutrophils. Endoscopy revealed atrophic gastritis. Deficiency of which factor is likely to be responsible for his condition?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin E","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":true},{"option":"Riboflavin","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Pyridoxine","bool":false}],"id":487},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 2-year-old boy presents with a history of anemia. His spleen is just palpable. Lab findings reveal Hb=10 gm/dL, MCV=67 fL, high HbA2 (7%), normal HbF, and a normal iron profile. Which of the following best corresponds to this clinical picture?","answers":[{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-thalassemia minor","bool":true},{"option":"Alpha-thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-thalassemia major","bool":false}],"id":488},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 25-year-old pregnant woman is found to have microcytic anemia during her antenatal visits. Her Hb is 7 mg/dL with an MCV of 66 fL. Which of the following is the single best test for the confirmation of iron deficiency anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Serum ferritin levels","bool":true},{"option":"Transferrin saturation","bool":false},{"option":"Total iron binding capacity (TIBC)","bool":false},{"option":"Serum iron levels","bool":false},{"option":"Hb electrophoresis","bool":false}],"id":489},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 57-year-old man presents with hypertrophy of gums and is diagnosed with acute myeloid leukemia (AML). Which of the following is characteristic of this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Auer rods","bool":true},{"option":"Ringed sideroblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Reed-Sternberg cells","bool":false},{"option":"Burr cells","bool":false},{"option":"Howell Jolly bodies","bool":false}],"id":490},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 34-year-old woman presents to the clinic with pallor, jaundice, and splenomegaly. Her complete blood count shows Hb 9 g/dL and MCV 107 fL. Direct Coomb's test is positive. She is diagnosed with warm autoimmune hemolytic anemia and treated with steroids, but the patient does not respond. Which of the following is the next best step in management?","answers":[{"option":"Transfusion","bool":false},{"option":"Azathioprine","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclophosphamide","bool":false},{"option":"Rituximab","bool":true},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":false}],"id":491},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 60-year-old woman presents with a 4-month history of progressive lethargy and recurrent throat infections. Recently, she developed gum bleeding and noticed purpura all over her body. She is anemic, but the remainder of the examination is normal. Investigations show Hb 7 g/dL, white cell count 83000/uL, and platelets 18000/uL. Bone marrow biopsy shows hypercellular marrow with a decrease in normal precursor cells.; 85% of the cells are myeloblasts. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":492},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 50-year-old man presents to the clinic with marked heaviness in the left hypochondrium. He has also had experienced early satiety for 3 months. On examination, the liver is enlarged, 3 cm below the costal margin amd the spleen is massively enlarged up to the umbilicus. Considering myelofibrosis as a diagnosis, which of the following is the only approved treatment?","answers":[{"option":"Immunotherapy","bool":false},{"option":"Interferon","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow transplantation","bool":false},{"option":"Ruxolitinib","bool":true},{"option":"Platelet aggregation inhibitor","bool":false}],"id":493},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 79-year-old woman presents to the emergency department with complaints of confusion, headache, and tinnitus. Her general practitioner has recently started her on an analgesic; the physician on duty is worried she may have taken too much. Which of the following would most likely explain her symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Paracetamol","bool":false},{"option":"Mefanamic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Codeine","bool":false},{"option":"Diclofenac sodium","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":true}],"id":494},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 68-year-old woman comes to the physician because of a history of easy fatigability and back pain. On examination, she is anemic and has tender bones. Her initial investigations show Hb 9.8 g/dL, MCV 84 fl, platelets 141 x 10^3/L, creatinine 2.3 mg/dL, ALP 84 IU, and SGPT 32 IU. Bone scan shows lytic lesions. Which of the following is the next best step in diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Serum protein electrophoresis","bool":true},{"option":"Urinary immune fixation","bool":false},{"option":"Serum immune fixation","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow biopsy","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary protein electrophoresis","bool":false}],"id":495},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 25-year-old female is diagnosed with porphyria variegate. Which of the following may be included as part of the specific management of this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Courses of venesection","bool":false},{"option":"Use of beta carotene","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous glucose as provision of 55 KJ per day","bool":false},{"option":"Avoidance of agents that can precipitate the condition","bool":true},{"option":"Use of sunscreens","bool":false}],"id":496},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 40-year-old man presents with easy fatigability. Investigations reveal hemoglobin (Hb) - 9 g/dL, mean corpuscular volume (MCV) - 105 fL, and spherocytes on peripheral blood film. Which of the following is the most common abnormality in hereditary spherocytosis?","answers":[{"option":"Protein 4.1 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Adducin deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-spectrin deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Alpha-spectrin deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Glycophorin C deficiency","bool":false}],"id":497},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 45-year-old male presents to you with complaints of early satiety and heaviness for the past 2 months. He also gives history of blurring of vision and severe headache for the past week. His labs show hemoglobin - 10.1 mg/dL, white blood cells - 79,000/mm3, platelets - 950,000 and left myeloid shift on peripheral smear. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Myelofibrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia vera rubra","bool":false},{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Essential thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":true}],"id":498},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy presents to you with a complaint of severe pain in his hands and feet. He is febrile, mildly jaundiced, and dehydrated. Labs show hemoglobin 0 5.6 gm/dL, reticulocyte count - 8%, total bilirubin - 2.5 mg, SGPT - 20. Family history is significant for a similar illness in his brother 1 year ago. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell trait","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute hepatitis","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell disease with vaso-occlusive crisis","bool":true}],"id":499},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is true regarding paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH)?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombosis is uncommon in PNH","bool":false},{"option":"Flow cytometry does not help in diagnosis","bool":false},{"option":"It does not progress to myelodysplasia or acute myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"It causes persistent hemoglobinuria","bool":false},{"option":"It can be suspected in confusing cases of hemolytic anemia or pancytopenia","bool":true}],"id":500},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 16-year-old male presents to you with complaints of fatigue, backache, leg pain, and fever. His labs show hemoglobin of 7 g/dL. Which of the following is the definitive diagnostic test for sickle cell anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Genetic screening of parents","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle solubility test","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle shaped cells on blood film","bool":false},{"option":"Reticulocytosis","bool":false}],"id":501},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"An 18-year-old boy presents to the clinic and you observe on examination rubbery lymph nodes in the cervical and axillary region, along with a history of weight loss for the past 4 months. Which of the following is the gold standard test for establishing the diagnosis of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Lymph node biopsy","bool":true},{"option":"CT scan abdomen","bool":false},{"option":"CT scan neck","bool":false},{"option":"CT scan chest","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow biopsy","bool":false}],"id":502},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is a poor source of folic acid?","answers":[{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Eggs","bool":true},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Bananas","bool":false},{"option":"Green leafy vegetable","bool":false}],"id":503},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is not an indication of anticoagulation therapy?","answers":[{"option":"Intracardiac thrombus","bool":false},{"option":"Internal carotid artery thrombus","bool":false},{"option":"Protein C or protein S deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Acute stroke secondary to hypertension","bool":true},{"option":"Stroke resulting from atrial fibrillation","bool":false}],"id":504},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2020"],"question":"A 65-year-old man presents to the hematology outpatient department with a 6 months history of tiredness, weight loss, and shortness of breath. On examination, there is massive splenomegaly but no lymphadenopathy. Lab investigations show hemoglobin - 9.8 g/dL, white blood cells - 240,000/mm3, and platelets - 458,000/mm3. Peripheral blood film shows increased number of neutrophils and myelocytes with prominent basophils and normocytic normochromic red blood cells. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic lymphocytic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myeloid leukemia","bool":false}],"id":505},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 19-year-old girl presents to the office with non-tender, rubbery, enlarged cervical lymph nodes. She also has a low-grade fever and her complete blood count is normal. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Acute leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Non-Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberculoid lymphadenitis","bool":false}],"id":506},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"What is the composition of adult hemoglobin?","answers":[{"option":"Alpha 2, beta 2","bool":true},{"option":"Alpha 2, delta 2","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha 2, epsilon 2","bool":false},{"option":"Zeta 2, epsilon 2","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha 2, gamma 2","bool":false}],"id":507},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of these factors can lead to poor tissue oxygenation?","answers":[{"option":"Polycythemia","bool":false},{"option":"Right shift of hemoglobin curve","bool":false},{"option":"Poor blood flow","bool":true},{"option":"Increased hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Increased blood volume","bool":false}],"id":508},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of these terms best explain the pancytopenia observed in aplastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Splenomegaly","bool":false},{"option":"Immunodeficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Neoplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow failure","bool":true},{"option":"Infection","bool":false}],"id":509},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"An 11-year-old girl presents with a petechial rash all over her body. Her bleeding time and activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) are prolonged but the prothrombin time (PT) is normal. Her sister also suffers from a similar condition. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":true},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Acute leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false}],"id":510},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following chromosomes contain the gene for the beta-globin chain of hemoglobin?","answers":[{"option":"11","bool":true},{"option":"14","bool":false},{"option":"3","bool":false},{"option":"16","bool":false},{"option":"9","bool":false}],"id":511},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which type of hemolysis characterizes paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH)?","answers":[{"option":"Both intra and extravascular hemolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Intravascular hemolysis","bool":true},{"option":"Extravascular hemolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Intramedullary hemolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Splenic hemolysis","bool":false}],"id":512},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 16-year-old boy, known case of hemophilia, injures himself while playing football and develops hemarthrosis in his right knee. What is the best treatment option?","answers":[{"option":"Recombinant factor 8 + bed rest + splint","bool":true},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Injection of Vitamin K","bool":false},{"option":"Recombinant factor 8","bool":false},{"option":"Tranexamic acid","bool":false}],"id":513},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of these indices is best for determining the race of a person?","answers":[{"option":"Ischiopubic index","bool":false},{"option":"Intermembral index","bool":false},{"option":"Medullary index of hair","bool":false},{"option":"Cephalic index","bool":true},{"option":"Humero-femoral index","bool":false}],"id":514},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"What do flow cytometry results show in paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria?","answers":[{"option":"Single type of cell population showing CD55+, CD59-","bool":false},{"option":"Two types of cell populations: one CD55-, CD59- and second CD55+, CD59+","bool":true},{"option":"Single type of cell population showing CD55+, CD59+","bool":false},{"option":"Single type of cell population showing CD55-, CD59+","bool":false},{"option":"Single type of cell population showing CD55-, CD59-","bool":false}],"id":515},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of these is a common manifestation of antiphospholipid syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Mouth ulcers","bool":false},{"option":"Raynaud phenomenon","bool":false},{"option":"Arthritis","bool":false},{"option":"Alopecia","bool":false},{"option":"Recurrent abortions","bool":true}],"id":516},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of these is a direct thrombin inhibitor?","answers":[{"option":"Abciximab","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Rivoraxaban","bool":false},{"option":"Dabigatran","bool":true},{"option":"Heparin","bool":false}],"id":517},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of these drugs binds to ADP receptors on platelets and thus inhibits platelet aggregation?","answers":[{"option":"Abciximab","bool":false},{"option":"Dabigatran","bool":false},{"option":"Cilostazol","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":true},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false}],"id":518},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 17-year-old boy presents to the office with complaints of weakness and shortness of breath. On examination, he appears to have jaundice and also has splenomegaly. He was treated for malaria one week ago. Which test can be done to determine the cause of anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Karyotype","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"Liver function tests","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) test","bool":true},{"option":"Hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":false}],"id":519},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 4-year-old boy has a form of microcytic, hypochromic anemia. His skull X-ray shows a crew-cut appearance. Which form of thalassemia is most likely in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Alpha thalassemia minor","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha thalassemia minima","bool":false},{"option":"Beta thalassemia major","bool":true},{"option":"Hemoglobin H disease","bool":false},{"option":"Beta thalassemia minor","bool":false}],"id":520},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of these terms best describes the characteristics/features of disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)?","answers":[{"option":"Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia (MAHA) + uremia","bool":false},{"option":"Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia (MAHA) + coagulopathy","bool":true},{"option":"Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia (MAHA)","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia (MAHA) + neurological symptoms","bool":false}],"id":521},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"What is the shape of entry wounds formed as a result of stabbing?","answers":[{"option":"Elliptical","bool":true},{"option":"Circular","bool":false},{"option":"Linear","bool":false},{"option":"Irregular","bool":false},{"option":"Puckered","bool":false}],"id":522},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"During the examination of a dead body, greenish discoloration in the right iliac fossa is seen. The abdomen is distended and the limbs are rigid. What term best describes the condition?","answers":[{"option":"Heat stiffening","bool":false},{"option":"Rigor mortis","bool":false},{"option":"Cadaveric spasm","bool":false},{"option":"Cold stiffening","bool":false},{"option":"Gas stiffening","bool":true}],"id":523},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of these methods of tattoo removal does not leave a scar?","answers":[{"option":"Electrolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Carbon dioxide snow","bool":false},{"option":"Dermabrasion","bool":false},{"option":"Caustic substances","bool":false},{"option":"Laser beam","bool":true}],"id":524},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 2-year-old boy presents with frontal and parietal bossing and a history of severe pallor for 1 month. His mother and father are first cousins. He has another sibling who has had blood transfusions. Hemoglobin electrophoresis shows an HbA1 of 15 percent and HbF of 85 percent. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hemoglobin Barts","bool":false},{"option":"Beta thalassemia major","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell disease","bool":false},{"option":"Beta thalassemia minor","bool":false},{"option":"Hemoglobin H disease","bool":false}],"id":525},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"What is the screening test of choice for deep venous thromboembolism?","answers":[{"option":"Doppler ultrasound","bool":false},{"option":"D-dimer","bool":true},{"option":"Computed tomography (CT) scan","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography (CT) angiography","bool":false},{"option":"MRI","bool":false}],"id":526},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of these terms best describes thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura?","answers":[{"option":"Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia (MAHA) plus neurologic symptoms and thrombocytopenia","bool":true},{"option":"Macroangiopathic hemolytic anemia (MAHA)","bool":false},{"option":"Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia (MAHA) plus coagulopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia (MAHA)","bool":false},{"option":"Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia (MAHA) plus thrombocytopenia","bool":false}],"id":527},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 12-year-old girl is sent for age determination. On which part of the body will the X-ray be performed?","answers":[{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Skull","bool":false},{"option":"Hand and wrist","bool":true},{"option":"Sternum","bool":false},{"option":"Shoulder","bool":false}],"id":528},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"What is the correct definition of anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Decreased total blood volume","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased WBC count","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased total red blood cell mass","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased platelet count","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased circulating red blood cell mass","bool":true}],"id":529},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"What is the mode of action of warfarin?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibition of ADP receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of factor Xa","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of vitamin K epoxide reductase","bool":true},{"option":"Inhibition of thrombin","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of COX enzymes","bool":false}],"id":530},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which medication can commonly lead to a hypercoagulable state?","answers":[{"option":"Diphenydramine","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Oral contraceptive pill","bool":true},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Antibiotics","bool":false}],"id":531},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which type of anemia is associated with Plummer-Vinson syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":532},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 24-year-old male presents to the office with an enlarging lump on his neck. Lymph node biopsy reveals lymphocytic infiltration in the germinal center along with tingible body macrophages in a 'starry sky' appearance. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Diffuse large B cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Follicular lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Burkitt lymphoma","bool":true}],"id":533},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 15-year-old child presents with low-grade fever and a mass on the right side of the neck which has been enlarging for the past two weeks. The mass is an enlarged lymph node in the anterior cervical chain. It is firm, non-tender, and rubbery. Which test needs to be ordered to confirm the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Ultrasound neck","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph node biopsy","bool":true},{"option":"CT scan","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow aspiration and trephine biopsy","bool":false},{"option":"PET scan","bool":false}],"id":534},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which stage of erythropoiesis has a condensed nucleus with 34% hemoglobin and no endoplasmic reticulum?","answers":[{"option":"Reticulocyte","bool":true},{"option":"Polychromatic erythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Basophilic erythroblast","bool":false},{"option":"Normoblast","bool":false},{"option":"Orthochromatic erythroblast","bool":false}],"id":535},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A child presented with the complaint of right armpit pain in the outpatient department of a hospital. On examination, the doctor noticed an abrasion on his forearm. A biopsy was suggested which revealed stellate necrotizing granuloma. Which of the following could be responsible for that?","answers":[{"option":"Epstein-Barr virus","bool":false},{"option":"Staphylococcus aureus","bool":false},{"option":"Cytomegalovirus","bool":false},{"option":"Yersinia pestis","bool":false},{"option":"Bartonella","bool":true}],"id":536},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"According to WHO classification, how many categories is myelodysplastic syndrome divided into?","answers":[{"option":"7","bool":false},{"option":"4","bool":false},{"option":"6","bool":true},{"option":"5","bool":false},{"option":"8","bool":false}],"id":537},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"What is the maximum amount of hemoglobin that can be concentrated in the red blood cell fluid?","answers":[{"option":"37 g/dL","bool":true},{"option":"15 g/dL","bool":false},{"option":"19 g/dL","bool":false},{"option":"10 g/dL","bool":false},{"option":"25 g/dL","bool":false}],"id":538},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"What is the mean age of occurrence of myelodysplastic syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"40","bool":false},{"option":"60","bool":false},{"option":"80","bool":false},{"option":"50","bool":false},{"option":"70","bool":true}],"id":539},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 55-year-old male has severe lumbar vertebral pain. His complete blood count shows normocytic normochromic anemia with a markedly raised erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR). The clinical diagnosis by the physician is multiple myeloma. Assuming that the clinical diagnosis is correct, what will be the most characteristic finding on the peripheral film of his peripheral smear?","answers":[{"option":"Tear drop cells","bool":false},{"option":"Fragmented RBCs","bool":false},{"option":"Rouleaux formation","bool":true},{"option":"Macro-ovalocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Target cells","bool":false}],"id":540},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following factors is required for red blood cell maturation?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Iron","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false},{"option":"Thiamine","bool":false}],"id":541},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following chromosomal abnormality is not observed in myelodysplastic syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Deletion of 18q","bool":true},{"option":"Trisomy 8","bool":false},{"option":"Complex karyotype","bool":false},{"option":"Monosomy 5/ deletion of 5q","bool":false},{"option":"Monosomy 7/ deletion of 7q","bool":false}],"id":542},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following chromosomal abnormalities is absent in chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL) or small lymphocytic lymphoma (SLL)?","answers":[{"option":"Translocation 14:18","bool":true},{"option":"Deletion of 13q","bool":false},{"option":"Deletion of 11q","bool":false},{"option":"Deletion of 17p","bool":false},{"option":"Trisomy 12q","bool":false}],"id":543},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"The age of a male needs to be determined. Dental X-ray reveals mixed dentition and an examination of the oral cavity reveals that his wisdom tooth has erupted. What is the approximate age of this person?","answers":[{"option":"18+ years","bool":false},{"option":"15+ years","bool":false},{"option":"20+ years","bool":false},{"option":"17+ years","bool":true},{"option":"25+ years","bool":false}],"id":544},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A child has had a fever for 15 days. He has been taking antipyretics and antibiotics. His complete blood count report shows leukopenia and absolute neutropenia. What would be the cause of neutropenia?","answers":[{"option":"Congenital neutropenia","bool":false},{"option":"Drug-induced neutropenia","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Deficiency of vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotherapy","bool":false}],"id":545},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the cause of Henoch-Schonlein purpura?","answers":[{"option":"Anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Vasculitis","bool":true},{"option":"Polycythemia","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false}],"id":546},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"What is the composition of hemoglobin A2 (HbA2)?","answers":[{"option":"α2, δ2","bool":true},{"option":"γ2, ε2","bool":false},{"option":"α2, γ2","bool":false},{"option":"β2, γ2","bool":false},{"option":"α2, β2","bool":false}],"id":547},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"What is the mechanism of action of dipyridamole?","answers":[{"option":"Irreversibly inhibiting binding of adenosine diphosphate (ADP) to its receptors on platelets","bool":false},{"option":"Blocking the binding of fibrinogen to von Willebrand factor","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibiting the activation of glycoprotein (GP) receptor llb/llla receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Interacting with arginine glycine aspartic acid sequence of fibrinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Increasing cAMP by inhibiting nucleotide phosphodiesterase","bool":true}],"id":548},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"How does the bleeding diathesis due to vascular disorder appear?","answers":[{"option":"Joint deformity","bool":false},{"option":"Hematoma","bool":false},{"option":"Tachycardia","bool":false},{"option":"Soft issue","bool":false},{"option":"Petechiae and purpura","bool":true}],"id":549},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common type of mutation seen in β thalassemia?","answers":[{"option":"Splicing mutation","bool":true},{"option":"Chain terminator mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Translocation","bool":false},{"option":"Gene deletion","bool":false},{"option":"Promoter region mutation","bool":false}],"id":550},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Due to which of the following preformed antibodies is the reaction caused in acute hemolytic reaction?","answers":[{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":true},{"option":"IgE","bool":false}],"id":551},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following conditions is known to cause ineffective intramedullary hematopoiesis and pancytopenia?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":false},{"option":"Renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"Myelodysplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Hypersplenism","bool":false}],"id":552},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A child is brought to the clinic by his parents with a complaint of fatigue. His parents further inform about their family history of blood disorder. His laboratory results show hemoglobin 9.6 mg/dL, reticulocytes 7%, and mean corpuscular volume (MCV) 87 fl. His blood smear shows the presence of spherocytes. What is the possible diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"G6PD deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell disease","bool":false},{"option":"Myeloproliferative disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":553},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Owl-like appearance is found in which cells present in Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Teardrop cells","bool":false},{"option":"Reed-Sternberg cells","bool":true},{"option":"Heinz bodies","bool":false},{"option":"Bite cells","bool":false},{"option":"Spur cells","bool":false}],"id":554},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following drugs is given in chronic granulomatous disease?","answers":[{"option":"Interferon gamma","bool":true},{"option":"Interferon beta","bool":false},{"option":"Telbivudine","bool":false},{"option":"Interferon alpha","bool":false},{"option":"Trastuzumab","bool":false}],"id":555},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"In beta-thalassemia major, which of the following is observed?","answers":[{"option":"Precipitation of delta chains","bool":false},{"option":"Precipitation of gamma chains","bool":false},{"option":"Precipitation of zeta chains","bool":false},{"option":"Precipitation of beta chains","bool":false},{"option":"Precipitation of alpha chains","bool":true}],"id":556},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A 50-year-old man has large-sized red blood cells and hemoglobin is also below normal. Which of the following will he be prescribed?","answers":[{"option":"Iron","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin D","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin  C","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid","bool":true}],"id":557},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Deficiency of which of the following comes with damage to myelin sheath?","answers":[{"option":"Folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin D","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":true},{"option":"Iron","bool":false}],"id":558},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is incorrect about aspirin?","answers":[{"option":"It causes exacerbation of asthma","bool":false},{"option":"It irreversibly inhibits cyclooxygenase","bool":false},{"option":"It is the only antiplatelet agent that irreversibly inhibits platelet function","bool":false},{"option":"Low dose aspirin works best when used prophylactically","bool":false},{"option":"High dose aspirin works best when used prophylactically","bool":true}],"id":559},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2021"],"question":"A primigravida presents to the antenatal clinic at 10 weeks gestation for her first visit. Her blood group is B- and she has no history of abortions or miscarriages. What is the initial test that will be done?","answers":[{"option":"Husband’s blood group","bool":true},{"option":"Antibody titers","bool":false},{"option":"Direct Coomb’s test","bool":false},{"option":"Amniocentesis","bool":false},{"option":"Indirect Coomb’s test","bool":false}],"id":560},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"An 18-year-old female patient was brought to the outpatient department with a complaint of on-and-off fever for 6 months and lymphadenopathy. On biopsy, a diagnosis of Hodgkin lymphoma was made. Which of the following cells are the characteristic diagnostic cell in Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Monocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Reed sternberg cells","bool":true},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false}],"id":561},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 32-year-old male came to the outpatient department complaining of fever, fatigue, weakness, weight loss, and night sweats. His blood report shows Hb: 9mg/dl, WBC: 82x 10E9, and platelets: 84x 10E9. Peripheral film review showed 69% blast cells. The patient was advised of bone marrow aspirate, trephine biopsy, and cytogenetics testing. In leukemic presentations, one of the following cells replaces the normal bone marrow cells to make it hypercellular?","answers":[{"option":"Lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Blast cells","bool":true},{"option":"Metamyelocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Myelocytes","bool":false}],"id":562},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 72-year-old male came to the outpatient department complaining of fever, fatigue, weakness, weight loss, and night sweats. His blood report shows Hb: 8 mg/dl, WBC: 3.5 x 10E9, and platelets: 90 x 10E9. Peripheral film review showed dysplastic neutrophils. The patient was advised of bone marrow aspirate, trephine biopsy, and cytogenetics testing. Which of the following is not the morphological feature of dysplastic syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"More than 20% blast cells","bool":true},{"option":"Pseudo-Pegler-Huet cells","bool":false},{"option":"Nuclear budding abnormalities","bool":false},{"option":"Ring sideroblasts","bool":false},{"option":"Megaloblastoid maturation","bool":false}],"id":563},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"which of the following cell types is a precursor to platelets?","answers":[{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Megakaryocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Histiocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Erythroid precursors","bool":false},{"option":"Myeloid precursors","bool":false}],"id":564},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 25-year-old female patient comes to the outpatient department with a history of easy bruising and prolonged bleeding after a minor cut. Upon history, she also told the doctor that her siblings have a similar problem. What are the initial tests that should be done to screen for bleeding disorders?","answers":[{"option":"Complete blood count, Fibrinogen, PT, APTT","bool":true},{"option":"Bleeding time, factor assay, bone trephine","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count, bleeding time, factor VIII level.","bool":false},{"option":"Bleeding time, complete blood count, PT/APTT","bool":false},{"option":"Factor assay, complete blood count, thrombin time","bool":false}],"id":565},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following hormone is produced by the liver for the synthesis of platelets from megakaryocytes?","answers":[{"option":"Thyroxin","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombopoietin","bool":true},{"option":"Erythropoitin","bool":false},{"option":"Corticosteroids","bool":false},{"option":"Growth hormone","bool":false}],"id":566},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following enzymes is regulated by hepcidin?","answers":[{"option":"Hephaestin","bool":false},{"option":"Duodenal cytochrome","bool":false},{"option":"Divalent metal transporter","bool":false},{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferroportin","bool":true}],"id":567},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 15-year-old female, diagnosed with hereditary spherocytosis for 2 years, came to the outpatient department complaining of shortness of breath and bleeding from gum. Her hemoglobin is 6.6 g/ dl, her white blood count is 1.2x 10E9/l and her platelet count is 30 x10E9. Peripheral smear shows pancytopenia and reticulocytopenia. Which of the following complications must she have developed in relation to the problems mentioned above?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic crisis","bool":true},{"option":"G6PD defeciency","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Gall stones","bool":false}],"id":568},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 6-year-old girl is evaluated for anemia. Her blood report shows hemoglobin of 5g/dl with 7% reticulocyte. Her platelets and leukocytes are normal. Peripheral smear shows numerous spherocytes. Her physical examination revealed splenomegaly. Her mother also has a similar history. Based on the information given above, what diagnosis can we make?","answers":[{"option":"G6PD defeciency","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombosis with thrombocytopenia syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Hereitary spherocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":false}],"id":569},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which one of the following is a cause of inherited aplastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Fanconi anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Cytomegalovirus","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Immune mediated aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Epstein bar virus","bool":false}],"id":570},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Iron is delivered to body tissues bound to which of the following molecules?","answers":[{"option":"Transferrin","bool":true},{"option":"Hemoglobin","bool":false},{"option":"Hepcidin","bool":false},{"option":"Hemosiderin","bool":false},{"option":"Ferritin","bool":false}],"id":571},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A patient is receiving heparin by continuous intravenous infusion. The doctor is most likely to ask the nurse to monitor which of the following symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Tinnitus","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Vomiting","bool":false},{"option":"Gum bleeding","bool":true},{"option":"Deacreased pulse rate","bool":false}],"id":572},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A patient is on antiplatelet therapy and is about to undergo surgery, His doctor advised him to discontinue the antiplatelet and wait at least one week before undergoing the surgery. Which of the following drugs is the patient most likely taking?","answers":[{"option":"dipyridamole","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":true},{"option":"Amciximab","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false},{"option":"Cilostazol","bool":false}],"id":573},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following drugs directly binds to fibrin clots leading to breakdown of plasminogen?","answers":[{"option":"Fondaparinux","bool":false},{"option":"Desirudin","bool":false},{"option":"Alteplase (tPA)","bool":true},{"option":"Dabigatran","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false}],"id":574},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 2-year-old boy is brought to the outpatient department with the complaint of easy bruising all over the body for the past one year. He has no history of trauma. His right knee joint is now swollen. Lab reports show normal platelets, normal prothrombin time, Hb of 10 g/ dl. APTT is raised. What further investigation is required to confirm diagnosis.","answers":[{"option":"Factor V levels","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand factor","bool":false},{"option":"Factor X levels","bool":false},{"option":"Factor VIII levels","bool":true},{"option":"Factor II levels","bool":false}],"id":575},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 5-year-old girl is brought to the outpatient department with the complaint of recurrent episodes of epistaxis and gingival bleeding. On examination, she is pale and has bruise marks all over her body. Her lab reports show normal PT/ APTT, normal platelet count, and normal Hb levels in her body but her bleeding time is prolonged. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Von willebrand disease","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia A","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia B","bool":false}],"id":576},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy is brought to the emergency department with a complaint of fever and loose motion for the last 10 days. He has developed bruises all over his body since last night and is bleeding rectally. On examination, he is sick-looking with cold peripheries. His lab reports show delayed capillary refill with decreased platelets, prolonged prothrombin time, activated partial thromboplastin time, and raised D-dimers. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulopathy","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand's disease","bool":false},{"option":"Dysentery","bool":false}],"id":577},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 3-year-old boy is brought to the outpatient department with the complaint of bruises all over his body for the past 2 days. He is otherwise active and playful. Physical examination is unremarkable. Complete blood count shows the total count of platelet at 20,000. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Disseminated Intravascular coagulopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand's disease","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet function disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false}],"id":578},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 15-months old baby is brought to the clinic with the complaint of progressive pallor and edema all over his body. He has a history of loose motions 1 week back. The mother also complains that her child is passing less urine than normal. examinations show edema and anemia. Lab reports indicate hemoglobin of 6g/dl, platelets of 90,000, and increased levels of urea and creatinine in the blood. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Nephrotic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":true}],"id":579},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A nine-month-old baby presented to the outpatient department with a complaint of progressive pallor and failure to thrive for the past 4 months, his parents are first cousins. On examination, the baby is underweight at 5.6 kg, severely anemic, with mild jaundice, and hepatosplenomegaly. Complete blood count indicates Hb= 5.2 g/dl, MCV= 65 fl, Hb-f= 85%, and TLC and platelets are normal. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Beta thalassemia major","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Beta thalassemia trait","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false}],"id":580},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 6-year-old boy develops sudden pallor and jaundice. He has taken fava beans. His Hb is 3.5 g/dl with normal TLC and platelets. Total bilirubin was 5 mg/dl, predominantly unconjugated and the reticulocyte count is > 20 hps. Urine is also positive for Hb. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Malaria","bool":false},{"option":"G6PD defeciency","bool":true},{"option":"Beta thalassemia major","bool":false},{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":false}],"id":581},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following indicates the earliest changes that occur in eyes after death?","answers":[{"option":"Sunken eye balls","bool":false},{"option":"dilated pupil","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of reflexes","bool":true},{"option":"Tache noirs spots","bool":false},{"option":"Segmentation of retinal vessels","bool":false}],"id":582},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A dying patient consented to a viscera transplantation after his death. When can a doctor take out the viscera for transplantation?","answers":[{"option":"On absent breath sounds","bool":false},{"option":"when ECG gets flat","bool":false},{"option":"After systemic death","bool":false},{"option":"After molecular death","bool":false},{"option":"After brain stem death","bool":true}],"id":583},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A child of pubertal age alleged to have been sexually assaulted was brought to the M/L section to determine the age. Which one of the following can be the best site for the X-ray to determine age.","answers":[{"option":"Shin","bool":false},{"option":"Foot and ankle","bool":false},{"option":"Knee","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Hands and Wrist","bool":true}],"id":584},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"The body of a 35-year-old was brought for autopsy, his relatives give a history of a tattoo, which was not found during the autopsy. Which of the following should be directed to find the tattoo ink?","answers":[{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Thyroid","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false}],"id":585},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"\"Chilotic line\" is a mathematical index which helps in determination of which of the following factors?","answers":[{"option":"Sex","bool":true},{"option":"Race","bool":false},{"option":"Age","bool":false},{"option":"Height","bool":false},{"option":"Stature","bool":false}],"id":586},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A young male is brought to emergency with the complaint of yellow discoloration of the sclera, after taking trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole that some general physician prescribed for some infection, the details of which are unknown. Laboratory reports show Hb of 8.5 g/dl, normal platelets, and TLC, total bilirubin is 4.2 mg/dl with predominant indirect hyperbilirubinemia. Liver enzymes are normal. The patient gives a previous history of recurring episodic jaundice and lethargy in the past. The given explanation best corresponds to which one of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase defeciency","bool":false},{"option":"Cold agglutinin disease","bool":false},{"option":"Paroxymal nocturnal hemoglobinurea","bool":false},{"option":"Drug induced hemolytic anemia","bool":true}],"id":587},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A young female presented to the outpatient department with sudden onset of abdominal distention for 1 week. On examination, there is a  fluid thrill, palmer erythema, and bilateral edema. Doppler ultrasound shows hepatic vein and inferior vena cava thrombosis. The thrombophilic profile shows a deficiency of proteins C and S. How long should we anticoagulate this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Life long","bool":false},{"option":"3 months","bool":false},{"option":"6 years","bool":false},{"option":"6 months","bool":true},{"option":"1 year","bool":false}],"id":588},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 28-year-old male gave a history of laparotomy due to intestinal perforation 1 month back, his mobility was reduced due to this condition and now he has developed right leg swelling and pain up to mid-thigh for the last 1 week which is progressing gradually. What will be the duration of anticoagulation in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"3 months","bool":true},{"option":"6 years","bool":false},{"option":"Life long","bool":false},{"option":"12 months","bool":false},{"option":"1 year","bool":false}],"id":589},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 36-year-old female with no known comorbidity comes to the outpatient department with a complaint of progressive right leg swelling, pain, and redness for the past 15 days. She also has a history of multiple 2nd-trimester miscarriages. What is the most probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Vasculitis","bool":false},{"option":"Conecctive tissue disease","bool":false},{"option":"Anti thrombin III defeciency","bool":false},{"option":"Antiphospholipid antibody syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Deep vein thrombosis","bool":false}],"id":590},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 30-year-old female with no known comorbidity comes to the outpatient department with a complaint of left lower limb swelling and redness for the last 15 days. She gives a history of multiple second-trimester miscarriages. What is the investigation of choice for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"X-ray knee","bool":false},{"option":"Doppler ultrasound of left leg","bool":true},{"option":"Ultrasound pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"D-dimer","bool":false}],"id":591},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 38-year-old female comes to the outpatient department with the complaint of easy bruisability, gum bleeding, and menorrhagia. The examination was unremarkable except for pallor. Lab reports show Hb at 6.5 g/dl, Total leukocyte count at 7.8/ cmm, and platelet count at 10,000 cmm, also reports are negative for antinuclear antibodies. Which of the following can be diagnosis for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Connective tissue disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic liver disease","bool":false}],"id":592},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 60-year-old patient with a history of hypertension and hyperlipidemia presents with fatigue, weight loss, and night sweats. Further evaluation reveals a high white blood cell count and splenomegaly. A diagnosis of myeloproliferative disorder is made. What is the drug of choice for the management of this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Ruxolitinib","bool":true},{"option":"Rituximab","bool":false},{"option":"Etanercept","bool":false},{"option":"Imatinib","bool":false}],"id":593},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"What is the first-line treatment option for immune thrombocytopenic purpura?","answers":[{"option":"RhD immunoglobulin","bool":false},{"option":"Fostamatinib","bool":false},{"option":"Steroids","bool":true},{"option":"Eltrombopag","bool":false},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":false}],"id":594},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 24-year-old male presents to the emergency with a new-onset blurring of vision with mild drooping of the eyelid. He reports being bitten by a snake in his village a few hours ago for which he only used a tourniquet and sucked out the venom. Which snakebite can lead to such a presentation?","answers":[{"option":"Cobra","bool":true},{"option":"Python","bool":false},{"option":"Copperhead","bool":false},{"option":"Anaconda","bool":false},{"option":"Cottonmouth","bool":false}],"id":595},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which one of these is the single best test for the diagnosis of polycythemia vera?","answers":[{"option":"JAK 2 mutation","bool":true},{"option":"Radiochromium labelled RBCs","bool":false},{"option":"Serum erythropoeitin","bool":false},{"option":"Serum LDH","bool":false},{"option":"Serum iron studies","bool":false}],"id":596},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 34-year-old woman presents to the office after a positive pregnancy test. Her last pregnancy was 8 years ago, which was a miscarriage. She is diagnosed case of APLA syndrome. Which of these is the best management option for her current pregnancy?","answers":[{"option":"Aspirin alone","bool":false},{"option":"Warfarin alone","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin+warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Heparin alone","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin+heparin","bool":true}],"id":597},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 33-year-old male presents to the emergency with the complaint of palpitations for the last few hours. Arrival EKG reveals atrial fibrillation with rapid ventricular rate. IV esmolol is administered and the patient achieves a normal heart rate. The hemodynamics are stable, and a transesophageal echocardiogram reveals no thrombus in the left atrium. Which of these is the next best step in management?","answers":[{"option":"IV verapamil","bool":false},{"option":"Defibrillation","bool":false},{"option":"Anticoagulation with heparin","bool":false},{"option":"Repeat beta blocker","bool":false},{"option":"DC cardioversion","bool":true}],"id":598},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"An 8-year-old male presents to the clinic with a history of recurrent episodes of abdominal pain, joint pain, and skin rashes. He also reports frequent episodes of fever and blood in the urine. The patient's mother says that these symptoms have been occurring for several months and have been getting worse over time.\r\n\r\nUpon examination, the patient is found to have joint pain and stiffness in his knees, ankles, and wrists. He also has a diffuse, non-pruritic rash on his lower legs and feet. The patient's abdomen is mildly tender to palpation, and he has difficulty standing and walking due to pain and stiffness in his joints. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"IgA nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Post streptococcal glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Henoch Schonlein purpura","bool":true},{"option":"Microscopic polyangitis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false}],"id":599},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 25-year-old man presents to the emergency department after being bitten by a snake while hiking. He reports severe pain and swelling at the site of the bite, as well as nausea, vomiting, and difficulty breathing. Physical examination reveals a puncture wound on his left ankle which is constantly oozing out blood, as well as significant edema and ecchymosis in the surrounding area. The patient's blood pressure is low and his heart rate is elevated. Lab counts reveal thrombocytopenia. What is the management of choice for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Prazosin","bool":false},{"option":"Fresh frozen plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet transfusion","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-Snake venom","bool":true},{"option":"Tetanus toxoid","bool":false}],"id":600},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"What is the investigation of choice for Von Willebrand disease?","answers":[{"option":"D-dimer levels","bool":false},{"option":"Serum ESR","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet count","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"Ristocetin cofactor assay","bool":true}],"id":601},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"What is the best treatment regimen for Hodgkin lymphoma?","answers":[{"option":"IAP","bool":false},{"option":"CDDP","bool":false},{"option":"ECF","bool":false},{"option":"ABVD regimen","bool":true},{"option":"CHOP regimen","bool":false}],"id":602},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 25-year-old man was rushed to the emergency department after an accidental fall from a motorbike. He was bleeding profusely and was examined for possible fractures and his x-ray report shows a fracture of the femur and the tibia. What kind of anemia is he at risk of?","answers":[{"option":"Normochromic and microcytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypochromic and microcytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypochromic and macrocytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypochromic and normocytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Normochromic normocytic anemia","bool":true}],"id":603},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"An old bedridden patient, who was diagnosed with deep vein thrombosis and had been prescribed warfarin as an anticoagulant for her condition a few years ago, was reported to the outpatient department with abnormally prolonged bleeding from the nose. She was given vitamin K as an antidote. What monitoring parameters are important to keep warfarin activity in check?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombin time","bool":false},{"option":"Aptt","bool":false},{"option":"Muscle enzymes and blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"PT/ INR","bool":true},{"option":"Clotting time","bool":false}],"id":604},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Two students were studying a case of a 40-year-old male patient with complaints of burning stomach pain relieved by taking food. He was diagnosed with peptic ulcer and was found to be anemic. His tests showed high ferritin levels along with high iron absorption. After medication, his iron absorption decreased. Which factor is synthesized by the liver and is responsible for regulating iron absorption by binding to ferroportin?","answers":[{"option":"Transferrin","bool":false},{"option":"Iron Responsive element","bool":false},{"option":"Hepcidin","bool":true},{"option":"Divalent metal transporter-1","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false}],"id":605},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which cells can perform multiple phagocytic events and remain functional for months?","answers":[{"option":"T lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":false},{"option":"B lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":true},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false}],"id":606},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A body of a person whose epidermis got burnt was brought to the forensic department for identification. Which of the following methods is the most feasible one?","answers":[{"option":"Go for DNA samplig","bool":false},{"option":"Sample can not be collected","bool":false},{"option":"Take fingerprints as dermis is not burnt","bool":true},{"option":"Take a teeth imprint","bool":false},{"option":"Collect burnt skin and take its print","bool":false}],"id":607},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 45-year-old woman presented to the emergency department with acute diarrhea and abdominal discomfort for 2 weeks. Stool culture shows parasitic eggs. Which cells would be raised in complete blood count?","answers":[{"option":"Eosinophils","bool":true},{"option":"Basophils","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"B-lymphocytes","bool":false}],"id":608},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A detective is searching for evidence at a crime scene when he encounters fingerprints on the doorknob. He takes the impressions for examination. Inspection reveals a pattern in which ridges run from left to right. What is the most likely fingerprint pattern in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Arch","bool":true},{"option":"Composite","bool":false},{"option":"Floral","bool":false},{"option":"Loop","bool":false},{"option":"Whorl","bool":false}],"id":609},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 24-year-old male met a psychologist at the airport. While discussing his life with the psychologist, he told him that he failed entrance exam tests multiple times as he has to work part-time jobs to support himself and his family because his father was on bed rest after a leg fracture. He appeared to be very hopeful that he will pass this time as his father has now started earning again and he got a lot of time to study for the upcoming exam. This case falls under what type of behavioral model?","answers":[{"option":"Dynamism","bool":false},{"option":"Occupational efficacy","bool":false},{"option":"Optimization","bool":true},{"option":"Social responsibility","bool":false},{"option":"Personal contentment","bool":false}],"id":610},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"What is the term used for different psychological mechanisms which are used to endure the challenges of life and result in acquiring and maintaining a state of health and normality?","answers":[{"option":"Control systems","bool":false},{"option":"Static health models","bool":false},{"option":"Defense mechanisms","bool":true},{"option":"Immune systems","bool":false},{"option":"Dynamic roles","bool":false}],"id":611},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 16-year-old boy presents to the emergency department with the complaint of swelling of the right knee joint after trivial trauma. History is significant for similar incidences over the past 4 years. Their family history is positive for a bleeding disorder. Investigations show hemoglobin - 10 g/dL, white cell count - 5,000/uL, and platelets - 200,000/uL. Which of the following correctly describes the above-mentioned condition? (prothrombin time=pt, active partial thrombin time= aptt )","answers":[{"option":"Normal pt prolonged, prolonged aptt , corrects on mixing","bool":true},{"option":"Prolonged pt, normal aptt, corrects on mixing","bool":false},{"option":"Prolonged pt, normal aptt, no correction on mixing","bool":false},{"option":"Normal pt, normal appt, no need to mix","bool":false},{"option":"Prolonged pt, prolonged aptt, no correction on mixing","bool":false}],"id":612},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 24-year-old male presents to the office with an enlarging lump on his neck. Lymph node biopsy reveals lymphocytic infiltration in the germinal center along with tingible body macrophages in a 'starry sky' appearance. The tumor exhibits a high mitotic index and Immunohistochemistry revealed t(8:14) translocation. What virus is present in almost all ⅙ cases?","answers":[{"option":"Human immunodefeciency virus","bool":false},{"option":"Epstein barr virus (EBV)","bool":true},{"option":"Influenza virus","bool":false},{"option":"Cytomegalovirus","bool":false},{"option":"Human herpes virus","bool":false}],"id":613},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 12-year-old girl was brought to the emergency department with complaints of continuous nose bleeding for one hour. On examination, she was afebrile and well. The general physical examination was unremarkable. She had no history except a self-limiting viral flu a few weeks back. What is the most appropriate diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Dengue","bool":false},{"option":"Acute immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":true},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":614},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A patient presented with lymphadenopathy to the clinic. A lymph node biopsy showed small lymphoid cells having a nodular appearance with prominent nucleoli. The cells were found to be CD5+ and Tdt negative. Further workup revealed (11:14) translocation. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Follicular lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Mantle zone lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Burkitt lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Marginal zone lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":615},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 25-year-old patient came to the outpatient department for her antenatal checkup. On examination she was pale. A complete blood picture reveals Hb 9 gm/dl with a hypochromic, microcytic picture. Which of the following statements is correct regarding the condition she is having?","answers":[{"option":"Screen for thalassemia trait","bool":false},{"option":"Investigate blood loss","bool":false},{"option":"Check for dietary habits","bool":true},{"option":"Order hemoglobin electrophoresis","bool":false},{"option":"Check for family history of similar disease","bool":false}],"id":616},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 50-year-old male has a flight to the USA and has started experiencing sudden pain in his left calf. What is the appropriate initial management?","answers":[{"option":"Ascard 75 mg tablets","bool":false},{"option":"Subcutaneous low molecular weight heparin","bool":true},{"option":"Warfarin","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior vena cava filter","bool":false},{"option":"DVT stocking","bool":false}],"id":617},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A man took anti-malarial prophylaxis before going to West Africa. Two to three weeks later he developed severe anemia along with hemoglobinuria. Which of the following is the correct statement regarding this condition?","answers":[{"option":"This disease is transferred by mosquitoes","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary disease common in females","bool":false},{"option":"This disease develops from a spontanueous mutation","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary disease common in males","bool":true},{"option":"This disease is endemic in West Africa","bool":false}],"id":618},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which one of the following diseases is associated with the deficiency of ADAMTS13?","answers":[{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP)","bool":true},{"option":"Hemophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false}],"id":619},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following will not be seen in case of multiple myeloma?","answers":[{"option":"Lytic bone lesions","bool":false},{"option":"Cast in urine and pus cells","bool":true},{"option":"Susceptibility to infection","bool":false},{"option":"Rouleux formation","bool":false},{"option":"Light chains excreted in urine","bool":false}],"id":620},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which one of the following statements is true for enoxaparin as compared to the rest of the low molecular weight heparins?","answers":[{"option":"APTT needs not to be monitored","bool":false},{"option":"Causes thrombocytopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Less teratogenic","bool":false},{"option":"Can be administered intravenously in the treatment of MI","bool":true},{"option":"Short action of duration","bool":false}],"id":621},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A lady presented to the outpatient department complaining of fatigue, shortness of breath, and a pale face. She got diagnosed with the case of malabsorption and megaloblastic anemia. Her reports show increased MCV. Antibodies against which of the following could be a reason for her anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Alpha cells of pancreas","bool":false},{"option":"Enterocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Chief cells of gastric mucosa","bool":false},{"option":"Intrinsic factor","bool":true},{"option":"Gliadin","bool":false}],"id":622},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 20-year-old man is rushed to the emergency department after getting into a severe bike accident. He needs a blood transfusion immediately as he suffered from severe blood loss. Which blood group is considered a universal donor?","answers":[{"option":"O negative","bool":true},{"option":"B positive","bool":false},{"option":"AB positive","bool":false},{"option":"O positive","bool":false},{"option":"AB negative","bool":false}],"id":623},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following cells are seen in megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Hyposegmented neutrophils","bool":false},{"option":"Hyper segmented polymorphonuclear leukocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Activated mast cells","bool":false},{"option":"Micro ovalocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Nucleated red blood cells","bool":false}],"id":624},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following correctly states the cause of megaloblastic anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Caused by the deficiency of vitamin B6 and folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Caused by the combined deficiency of vitamin B12 and folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Caused by the deficiency of vitamin B12 only","bool":false},{"option":"Caused by the deficiency of folic acid only","bool":false},{"option":"Caused by the deficiency of either vitamin B12 or folic acid","bool":true}],"id":625},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A man has an enlarged prostate gland which is palpable on digital rectal examination. He is diagnosed with prostatic adenocarcinoma and presents with anemia and pancytopenia. MCV is normal. Which of the following is the type of anemia seen in this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Aplastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Myelophthisic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia of chronic disease","bool":true},{"option":"Megaloblastic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Iron deficiency anemia","bool":false}],"id":626},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 6-year-old child has been diagnosed with hereditary spherocytosis and complained of an increased frequency of blood transfusions. Blood complete picture shows Hb = 6.5 gm/dL, reticulocyte count = 20%, TLC = 4000/mm³, platelets = 100,000/mm³. What will be the most appropriate treatment in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Corticosteroids with anti thymhocytic globulin","bool":false},{"option":"Splenectomy","bool":true},{"option":"Bone marrow transplant","bool":false},{"option":"Repeated transfusions with iron chelation","bool":false},{"option":"Hydroxyurea","bool":false}],"id":627},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A patient presented to the outpatient department with pallor and cyanosis of extremities. The doctor suspected him of a case of hemolysis and ordered investigations. He had both direct and indirect coomb test positive but only at 4°C and not at 37°C. Which of the following is the type of immunoglobulin responsible?","answers":[{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":true},{"option":"IgE","bool":false},{"option":"Both IgG and IgM","bool":false}],"id":628},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 77-year-old woman notices that petechiae appeared on the skin of her arms and legs over the past 3 weeks. On physical examination, she is afebrile and has no organomegaly. Laboratory studies show a normal prothrombin time and partial thromboplastin time. CBC shows hemoglobin of 12.7 g/dL, hematocrit of 37.2%, MCV of 80 μm3, platelet count of 276,000/mm3, and WBC count of 5600/mm3. Platelet function studies and fibrinogen levels are normal, and no fibrin split products are detectable. Which of the following best explains these findings?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"Macronodular cirrhosis","bool":false},{"option":"Meningococcemia","bool":false},{"option":"Metastatic carcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C deficiency","bool":true}],"id":629},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A clinical study of patients who inherit mutations that reduce the level of ankyrin, the principal binding site for spectrin, in the RBC membrane cytoskeleton shows an increased \r\nprevalence of chronic anemia with splenomegaly. For many patients, it is observed that splenectomy reduces the severity of anemia. This beneficial effect of splenectomy is most likely related to which of the following processes?","answers":[{"option":"Decrease in opsonization of RBCs and lysis in spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in deformability of RBCs within splenic sinusoids","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease in production of reactive oxygen species by splenic macrophages","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in splenic storage of iron","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease in splenic RBC sequestration and lysis","bool":true}],"id":630},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"Which of the following terms is used for over production of abnormal white blood cells?","answers":[{"option":"Leucopenia","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Polycythemia vera","bool":false},{"option":"Leukocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Leukemia","bool":true}],"id":631},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 16-year-old girl has had frequent nosebleeds since childhood. Her gums bleed easily, even with routine tooth brushing. She has experienced menorrhagia since menarche at the age of 13 years. On physical examination, there are no abnormal findings. Laboratory studies show hemoglobin, 14.1 g/dL; hematocrit, 42.5%; MCV, 90 μm3; platelet count, 277,400/mm3; and WBC count, 5920/mm3. Her platelets fail to aggregate in response to ADP, collagen, epinephrine, and thrombin. The ristocetin agglutination test result is normal. There is a deficiency of glycoprotein IIb/IIIa. Prothrombin time is 12 seconds, and partial thromboplastin time is 28 seconds.  What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Glanzmann thrombasthenia","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin C deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Immune thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false},{"option":"Von Willebrand disease","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":false}],"id":632},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 10-year-old child has experienced multiple episodes of pneumonia and meningitis with septicemia since infancy. Causative organisms include Streptococcus pneumoniae and Haemophilus influenzae. On physical examination, the child has no organomegaly and no deformities. Laboratory studies show hemoglobin of 9.2 g/dL, hematocrit of 27.8%, platelet count of 372,000/mm3, and WBC count of 10,300/mm3. Hemoglobin electrophoresis shows 1% hemoglobin A2, 7% hemoglobin F, and 92% hemoglobin S. Which of the following is the most likely cause of repeated infections in this child?","answers":[{"option":"Diminished hepatic synthesis of complement proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Impaired neutrophil production","bool":false},{"option":"Absent endothelial cell expression of adhesion molecules","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced synthesis of immunoglobulins","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of normal splenic function due to recurrent ischemic injury","bool":true}],"id":633},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A child had a history of typhoid fever for 15 days. He was given a number of antibiotics including chloramphenicol and antipyretics. His laboratory work shows neutropenia. What is the cause of the neutropenia?","answers":[{"option":"Autoimmune destruction","bool":false},{"option":"Overwhelming fungal infection","bool":false},{"option":"Splenomegaly sequestration","bool":false},{"option":"Drug induced neutropenia","bool":true},{"option":"Immunological mediated injury due to Systemic lupus erythmatosis","bool":false}],"id":634},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"An 11-year-old child has a history of easy bruising.  Since the age of 9 years, he experienced hemorrhaging around the pharynx that produced acute airway obstruction. Family history indicates that other male relatives have similar bleeding problems. Laboratory studies show hemoglobin, 13.1 g/dL; hematocrit, 39.2% (N= 40-54%); platelet count, 228,000/mm3; WBC count, 5950/mm3; prothrombin time, 13 seconds (N=12-14.8s); and partial thromboplastin time is 52 seconds (27-41s). A dilution of the patient’s plasma with normal pooled plasma corrects the partial thromboplastin time. Which of the following manifestations of this illness will most likely ensue without recombinant factor VIII therapy?","answers":[{"option":"Splenomegaly","bool":false},{"option":"Hemolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Hemarthroses","bool":true},{"option":"Conjunctival petechiae","bool":false},{"option":"Hemochromatosis","bool":false}],"id":635},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A young girl who is suffering from Epstein Barr viral disease has a positive Monospot test. What kind of immunoglobulins are these heterophile antibodies seen in this case?","answers":[{"option":"IgD","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"IgG","bool":false},{"option":"IgM","bool":true},{"option":"IgE","bool":false}],"id":636},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A dead body is brought to the mortuary, lower limbs are stiff, while the abdomen, chest, and upper body are relaxed. How much time has passed since death?","answers":[{"option":"12-24 hours","bool":false},{"option":"8-12 hours","bool":false},{"option":"4-8 hours","bool":false},{"option":"48-56 hours","bool":false},{"option":"36-48 hours","bool":true}],"id":637},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 62-year-old man has experienced vague abdominal discomfort accompanied by bloating and diarrhea for the past 6 months. On physical examination, there is a midabdominal firm mass. The stool is positive for occult blood. An abdominal CT scan shows a mass that was removed. Microscopically, the mass is composed of sheets of large lymphoid cells with large nuclei, prominent nucleoli, and frequent mitotic figures. The neoplastic cells mark with CD19+ and CD20+ and have the BCL6 gene rearrangement. Which of the following prognostic features are most applicable to this case?","answers":[{"option":"Indolent, survival of 7 to 9 years without treatment","bool":false},{"option":"Indolent, can be cured by chemotherapy","bool":false},{"option":"Indolent, often undergoes spontaneous remission","bool":false},{"option":"Aggressive, can be cured by chemotherapy","bool":true},{"option":"Aggressive, often transforms to acute leukemia","bool":false}],"id":638},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 55-year-old man felt a lump near his shoulder 1 week ago. On physical examination, there is an enlarged, non-tender, supraclavicular lymph node and an enlargement of the Waldeyer ring of oropharyngeal lymphoid tissue. There is no hepatosplenomegaly. CBC is normal except for findings of mild anemia. A lymph node biopsy specimen shows replacement by a monomorphous population of lymphoid cells that are twice the size of normal lymphocytes, with enlarged nuclei and prominent nucleoli. Immunohistochemical staining and flow cytometry of the node indicates that most lymphoid cells are CD19+, CD10+, CD3−, CD15−, and terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase negative (TdT−). A BCL6 gene mutation is present. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic lymphadenitis","bool":false},{"option":"Diffuse large B-cell lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Hodgkin lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Small lymphocytic lymphoma","bool":false}],"id":639},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 9-year-old boy has had increasing pain and swelling on the right side of his face over the past 8 months. On physical examination, there is a large, non-tender mass involving the mandible, which deforms the right side of his face. There is no lymphadenopathy or splenomegaly, and he is afebrile. A biopsy of the mass is performed and microscopic examination shows intermediate-sized lymphocytes with a high mitotic rate. A chromosome analysis shows a t(8;14) karyotype in these cells. The hemoglobin concentration is 13.2 g/dL, the platelet count is 272,000/mm3, and the WBC count is 5820/mm3. Infection with which of the following viruses is most likely to be causally related to the development of these findings?","answers":[{"option":"Epstein-Barr virus","bool":true},{"option":"Cytomegalovirus","bool":false},{"option":"Human papillomavirus","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatitis B virus","bool":false},{"option":"HIV","bool":false}],"id":640},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2022"],"question":"A 35-year-old man with a history of intravenous drug abuse has generalized lymphadenopathy. Which of the following tests would help in finding the cause of his lymphadenopathy?","answers":[{"option":"Ultrasonography","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow biopsy","bool":false},{"option":"HIV serology","bool":true},{"option":"Histopathology","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count (CBC)","bool":false}],"id":641},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the process of giving preformed antibodies or vaccines to a person?","answers":[{"option":"Active immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Passive immunity","bool":true},{"option":"Humoral immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Cell-mediated immunity","bool":false},{"option":"Immunization","bool":false}],"id":642},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"Which of these live attenuated vaccines is contraindicated during pregnancy?","answers":[{"option":"Rabies","bool":false},{"option":"MMR","bool":true},{"option":"Diphtheria","bool":false},{"option":"HBV","bool":false},{"option":"Tetanus","bool":false}],"id":643},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"In postmortem examination of the body, the tattoo marks disappear from the skin. Which of the following should be examined?","answers":[{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Heart","bool":false},{"option":"Thyroid gland","bool":false}],"id":644},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"For how long should the warfarin therapy be discontinued if a patient is given vitamin K?","answers":[{"option":"72 hours","bool":false},{"option":"48 hours","bool":false},{"option":"24 hours","bool":true},{"option":"12 hours","bool":false},{"option":"6 hours","bool":false}],"id":645},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"Mycobacterium cannot be gram stained because of the presence of which substance in its cell wall?","answers":[{"option":"Lipotechoic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Lipoproteins","bool":false},{"option":"Mycolic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Techoic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Polysaccharide","bool":false}],"id":646},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A skull is found to have oval orbits, a sharp chin, an obtuse angle of the mandible, and smooth facial contours. The skull is more likely to belong to which of the following options?","answers":[{"option":"Male","bool":false},{"option":"Neonate","bool":false},{"option":"Infant","bool":false},{"option":"Elderly","bool":false},{"option":"Female","bool":true}],"id":647},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A dead body is found with complete calcification of the third molar. Which of the following could be the age of this person before death?","answers":[{"option":"25 years","bool":true},{"option":"18 years","bool":false},{"option":"5 years","bool":false},{"option":"9 years","bool":false},{"option":"12 years","bool":false}],"id":648},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"In what part of the body does postmortem lividity develop if the body was floating in the water?","answers":[{"option":"Face","bool":false},{"option":"Back","bool":false},{"option":"No lividity","bool":true},{"option":"Arms","bool":false},{"option":"Trunk","bool":false}],"id":649},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A person is brought to the emergency department with shortness of breath and syncope and is identified to have angina. Which of the following anticoagulants should be given to the patient?","answers":[{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Enoxaparin","bool":true},{"option":"Idarucizumab","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false},{"option":"Alteplase","bool":false}],"id":650},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the most potent thrombolytic agent but causes an increased epitope presentation?","answers":[{"option":"Reteplase","bool":false},{"option":"Alteplase","bool":false},{"option":"Streptokinase","bool":true},{"option":"Tenecteplase","bool":false},{"option":"Urokinase","bool":false}],"id":651},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 45-year-old female with chronic hypertension presents to the outpatient\r\ndepartment with petechial rashes. Laboratory shows platelet counts of 50,000. The prothrombin time (PT) and partial thromboplastin time (PTT) are both in a normal range. However, the bleeding time is elevated. Which of the following is the cause of her condition?","answers":[{"option":"Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":true},{"option":"Hemolytic uremic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Disseminated intravascular coagulation","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow suppression","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura","bool":false}],"id":652},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 45-year-old male patient presents to the outpatient department with painless lymphadenopathy in the neck and axilla. He also reports experiencing night sweats, and unexplained weight loss for the past few weeks. On physical examination, the nodes are firm and non-tender. There is no evidence of hepatosplenomegaly. The lymph nodes are of different sizes. Which of the following can be a likely cause of his condition?","answers":[{"option":"Tuberculosis","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple myeloma","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic myeloid leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute lymphoblastic leukemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hodgkins lymphoma","bool":true}],"id":653},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A newborn feeds on cow milk 5 times a day. Which of the following can develop jaundice and pallor in this baby?","answers":[{"option":"Antibodies against cow milk","bool":true},{"option":"Low bioavailability","bool":false},{"option":"Low iron content","bool":false},{"option":"Low folic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Low absorption of milk","bool":false}],"id":654},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"Which of the following worm infestations cause severe anemia during pregnancy?","answers":[{"option":"Pinworms","bool":false},{"option":"Tapeworms","bool":false},{"option":"Hookworms","bool":true},{"option":"Ascariasis","bool":false},{"option":"Schistosoma infection","bool":false}],"id":655},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 7-year-old boy develops jaundice and severe anemia after consuming fava beans. Which of the following is the cause of his condition?","answers":[{"option":"Polycythemia vera","bool":false},{"option":"Thalassemia","bool":false},{"option":"G6PD deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Sickel cell anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false}],"id":656},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 25-year-old female is transfused blood. After two weeks, she presents to the outpatient department for a follow-up with anemia, fever, and chills. Her direct Coombs test is positive. Which of the following is the cause of her condition?","answers":[{"option":"Acute hemolytic reaction to minor groups","bool":false},{"option":"Delayed reaction to minor groups","bool":true},{"option":"Acute hemolytic reaction due to Rh group","bool":false},{"option":"Graft versus host disease","bool":false},{"option":"Delayed hemolytic reaction due to ABO blood group","bool":false}],"id":657},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A child presented in the outpatient department for a follow-up of his CBC report. His reports are as follows: hemoglobin = 4 g/dL, MCV = 49 fl. TLC and platelets were within the normal range. What is the next best investigation?","answers":[{"option":"Repeat CBC","bool":false},{"option":"Hb electrophoresis","bool":false},{"option":"Iron profile","bool":true},{"option":"Serum vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"Coombs test","bool":false}],"id":658},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A 31-year-old male presented to the outpatient department (OPD) with complaints of jaundice. On taking a detailed history it was found he is on anti-malarial drugs. What is the most likely cause of this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Hereditary spherocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"G6PD","bool":true},{"option":"Autoimmune hemolytic anemia","bool":false},{"option":"Acute liver failure","bool":false},{"option":"Sickle cell anemia","bool":false}],"id":659},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"What is the best test for disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC)?","answers":[{"option":"Decreased PT and PTT","bool":false},{"option":"Increased coagulation factors","bool":false},{"option":"D-dimer","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinogen and FDP","bool":true},{"option":"International normalized ratio (INR)","bool":false}],"id":660},{"info":["3rd-year/hematology/compiled","3rd-year/hematology/2023"],"question":"A child presented in the clinic with abdominal pain. His serum complement levels were normal. What is the most likely cause?","answers":[{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":false},{"option":"Membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Henoch-Schönlein purpura","bool":true},{"option":"Cryoglobulinemia","bool":false},{"option":"Post-streptococcal glomerulonephritis","bool":false}],"id":661}]
export default arr